<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dispute vpon communicating at our confused communions</title>
            <author>Calderwood, David, 1575-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118324</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853531</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853531</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18916</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18916)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1197:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dispute vpon communicating at our confused communions</title>
                  <author>Calderwood, David, 1575-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Successors of Giles Thorpe],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Anno 1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By David Calderwood.</note>
                  <note>Printers and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18916:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18916:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISPVTE VPON COMMVNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATING AT OVR <hi>Confuſed Communions.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>If I build againe the things which I deſtroyed, I make my ſelfe a tranſgreſſor. <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 2.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Yee did runne well, who did hinder you, that yee ſhould not obey the truth. This perſwaſion commeth not of him that calleth you. A litle leaven leaveneth the whole lumpe. <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. cap. 5. verſ. 7.8.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Remember from whence thou art fallen, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and do thy firſt works, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and will remoue thy Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick out of his place, except thou repent. <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 2.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>As many as deſire to make a faire ſhew in the fleſh, they conſtraine you to bee circumciſed; onely leaſt they ſhould ſuffer perſecution for the croſſe of Chriſt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 6.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed Anno</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:18916:2"/>
            <q>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſe yee, Meroz ſayeth the Angel of the lord: curſe ye bitterlie the inhabitants ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, becauſe they came not to the helpe of the Lord, to the help of the lord againſt the mightie, <bibl>Iudg. 5.23.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Curſed be he that maketh the blinde to goe out of the way, and al the people ſhal ſay Amen, <bibl>Deut. 27.18.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Who ſhal offend one of theſe litle ones which beleev in me, it were better for him that a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone were hanged about his neck and he were drowned in the depth of the ſea, <bibl>Matt. 18.6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Woe to the world, becauſe of offenſes. For it muſt needes be that offenſes muſt come: But woe to that man by whom the offenſe cometh, <bibl>Mat. 18.7.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18916:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of ſitting at the Lords table.</head>
            <p>IT was or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nerall aſſemblie hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en at E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inburgh the yeere 1564.<note place="margin">Sitting at ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municants, was not a Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution.</note> that miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs in miniſtration of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſhould uſe the order ſet down in our pſalme b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oks. This order requireth that the communicants ſit at table, and breake bread with other. This order hath beene univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and perpetuallie obſerved in our kirk from the firſt yeere of reformation and ſome yeeres before, not as an order depending upon the varieties of times, places, perſons, or the like circumſtances, as doe church orders, and conſtitutions, but as moſt agreeable to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of the firſt ſupper celebrated by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as may be ſeen in the firſt booke of diſcipline, and in two Rubricks in our pſalme bookes. In the laſt of the two Rubricks it is ſaid, that Chriſt commanded, that the communicants divide the elements among th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mſ lues In the booke of diſcipline it is ſaid. <hi>That it is plaine Chriſt Ieſus ſat at table with his diſciples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Christ &amp; his Apostles knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not but ſate at the first ſupper.</note> and therefore doe we judge that ſitting at a table is moſt convenient for that action.</p>
            <p>Chriſts uſual geſture in bleſsing bread at ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was ſitting, as we may ſee at <hi>Emaus Luk.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18916:3"/> and when he was to worke the miracle of the five loaves <hi>Matt.</hi> 14.13. while the diſciples were eating, and conſequentlie ſitting, as the moſt learned among the Ieſuites themſelves confeſſe, Chriſt tooke bread, and after he had given thanks, brake it. If they kneeled not at the thankſgiving, or bleſsing, there is no like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, that they kneeled in the act of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. If there had been anie change from one table geſture to another, from ſitting at the paſchal ſupper into ſtanding about the table, as the Iſraelites did at the firſt paſchal ſupper in Egypt, wold not the Euangeliſts have made mention of it? farre more, if there had been a change from all kinde of table geſture into kneeling a geſture of adoration, yea kneeling ſhould then have been the only lawful geſture i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtituted by Chriſt. For to what end alſo ſhould the change have been made. And ſo al that communicated ſitting either in the primitive kirk, or in the reformed ſhould have ſinned in ſo doing. When Chriſt gave the bread he ſaid, <hi>This is my bodie.</hi> The formaliſt wil not utter theſe words to the kneeler, when he delivereth the bread. When Chriſt gave the cuppe to the neereſt, he badde them divide it among themſelves. They could not then be kneeling. For how could kneeling, a geſture of adoration, conſiſt with dividing, which is not an act of adoration. As it is cleere that they kneeled not, ſo likewiſe that they ſtood not, for how could they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venientlie ſtand in the places, where they ſate leaning upon beds? Farther the Euangeliſts make no mention of ſtanding, but onlie ſay, that while they were
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18916:3"/> eating, Chriſt took bread.<note place="margin">On the Lords ſupper <hi>1.</hi> part. pag. <hi>136</hi>
               </note> Even <hi>Pierr du Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> ſayeth that <hi>the Apostles continued ſitting at the table to the verie end of the action.</hi> Who ever ſaid otherwiſe in anie age til this time?</p>
            <p>Examples in ſetting down of a patterne ſerve ordinarilie for direction in times to come,<note place="margin">Christ rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſitting the ordinarie ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture at reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions feasts.</note> if there be not ſome ſingular occaſion of the ſame, which will not agree to other times. But there was no ſingular occaſion of ſitting at the firſt ſupper. The waſhing of the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples feet, the putting on, and off of Chriſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per garment preceeded the ſecond ſervice of the paſchal ſupper, when as Chriſt was not yet come to the celebration of the euangelical. The eventide, the unleavened bread, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, the number of twelve, and other like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts, and circumſtances were but onlie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional, &amp; accidentarie to the Euangelicall ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, becauſe the legall ſupper to which they properly belonged, was celebrated immediatly before, and the laſt act of it changed into this ſupper. But ſitting was not a table geſture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the paſchal ſupper, and ſo occaſional, or accidentarie to the Euchariſtical. It was the common, and ordinarie geſture uſed at all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious feaſts both among the true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God, and Idolaters. To the feaſts after the ſacrifices the Apoſtle compareth this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian feaſt 1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 10. So, to ſpeake properlie Chriſt did not ſo much inſtitute this geſture at this ſupper, as ratifie and approve the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, and uſual. Yee wil ſay, that if we ought to follow this exemple we ſhould ſit leaning. It followeth not. Their geſture was a kinde of ſitting geſture, as Doctor <hi>Morton</hi> confeſſeth.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18916:4"/> And not onlie the Engliſh tranſlaters expreſſe it by the word ſitting but alſo the holie ghoſt in the holie language. A man may be ſaid to ſtand whether he ſtand upright, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aning to a wal, ſo ſitting. Our ſitting, and the Turk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and their ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting at the paſchal ſupper anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re analogicallie to other, and the diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rence is onlie national. Farth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to ſit was the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie geſture at religious feaſts, but to ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing was onlie occaſional, and acciden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arie to the Euangelical ſupper by reaſon of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> canon which was made before the day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſt, wherin manie diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rences were made betwixt the paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hal feaſt, and other r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ligious feaſts, and among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he reſt to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t forth the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lemnitie of this feaſt above others, it was ordained that they ſhould ſit after his maner a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this feaſt, and not at other except they pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſed. <hi>Quod in omnibus noctibus tam edentes qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m bibente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vel ſedemus, vel diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbimus, or accum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imus, in hac autem omnes d ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbimus, or accumbimus.</hi> They ſat of old even when the cuppe of praiſe was caried from hand to hand, and the cake of bread broken at the concl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſioun of the ſupper, And yet the concluſion of the paſch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l ſupper where they did eat to the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie of an olive, and leſſe then the quantitie of an egge was as ſhort, as the euangelical ſupper wherunto it was changed. Chriſt ledde the Apoſtles fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m their ſitting at table to the conſideration of their ſitting upon thrones, whereby we may not onlie collect that their geſture was a kind of ſitting geſture, but alſo that the end and uſe of their ſitting at table with him, was to note their fellowſhippe they had with him,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18916:4"/> and the dignitie, wherunto he had exalted them. Chriſt was as <hi>Ierome</hi> ſayeth both <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viva &amp; convivium,</hi> the foode that they eate, and a banqueter with them. By eating him as food is repreſented our union with him, as foode is united with the feeder, but by ſitting is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared our fellowſhip with him, as of ghueſts with the maſter of the feaſt.</p>
            <p>Howbeit ſitting had not bene the ordinarie table geſture at religious feaſts,<note place="margin">The Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick churches ſatt at table.</note> but a new ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, yet ſeeing it was an example not occaſional, or accidentarie but of free choiſe in ſetting down the patterne, it is a direction for our imitation, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves tooke it ſo, they continued this geſture after the firſt ſupper as a geſture moſt ſutable with the forme of a feaſt. When they cal this feaſt the table of the Lord, &amp; the ſupper of the Lord, it may very well be collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they uſed that geſture which was fit for a ſupper table. And beſide that a table is requiſite whatſoever be the matter of it, a boord, a bull hide, a plott of ground, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther high, or low, round, long, or ſquare. The love feaſts conjoyned with the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per could hardlie admitt the geſture of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſayeth <hi>Beza.</hi> The <hi>Corinthians</hi> fault was,<note place="margin">Contra Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium.</note> that neither at common meates,<note place="margin">Obed. pag. <hi>461.</hi>
               </note> nor at the Lords table they wold ſit together, but ſorted themſelves in factions, and companies,<note place="margin">Secund ſerm pag. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> ſayeth Doctor <hi>Bilſon</hi> Doctor <hi>Downame</hi> confeſſeth ſitting to receave the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>crament to have been vſed in the churches in the Apoſtles times.</p>
            <p>Howbeit the ſupper of the Lord ſoon after the dayes of the Apoſtles be ganne to be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">ſitting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued after the dayes of the Apostles Calv. inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. lib. cap. <hi>17.</hi> Homil. <hi>27.</hi> in <hi>1.</hi> cor. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18916:5"/> with ſome ruſt, as <hi>Mr. Calvine</hi> obſerveth, yet was this geſture continued in manie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and at ſome times vniverſallie obſerved. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> maketh mention of ſitting at Chriſts table <hi>Auguſtine</hi> inſinuateth no leſſe, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118. where he ſayeth that ſome mixed this feaſt with their other repaſts. <hi>M. Foxe</hi> thus writeth of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> whom <hi>Beza</hi> calleth the pure ſeede of the ancient church. <hi>Concerning the ſupper of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument <hi>1.</hi> Volum. pag. <hi>209.</hi> edit. <hi>1610.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>their faith was, that it was ordained to be eaten, and not to be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and worſhipped; for a memoriall, and not for a ſacrifice; to ſerue for the preſent miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and not for reſervation; to be receiued at table, not to be carried out of doores, according to the vſe of the primitive church, when they vſed to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate ſitting. And this they prove both by an old chronicle, called Chronica geſtorum, as alſo by ancient Origen.</hi> When the manner of celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after the pattern of the firſt ſupper beganne to be neglected almoſt everie where, and, as <hi>Mr. Calvine</hi> ſayeth, was changed into a Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh forme of ſacrificing, it was appointed, that the ſupper of the Lord ſhould be celebrated according to the inſtitution vpon the thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day before <hi>Easter,</hi> which the ancients called <hi>Caena Domini,</hi> and is now called <hi>Maundi Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> becauſe vpon that day the Lords ſupper was firſt celebrated. Al faithful Chriſtians (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept offenders) were wont to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate upon this day,<note place="margin">De conſecrat Diſt. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> as may be ſeen in <hi>Gratians</hi> Decree. <hi>In caena Domini a quibuſdam perceptio euch. triſtia negligitur, quae quoniam in eadam die ab omnibus fidelibus (exceptis ijs quibus pro gravibus crimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inhibitum eſt) percipienda ſit, eccleſiaſticus
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18916:5"/> vſus demonſtrant.</hi> Now the gloſſe vpon that place that hath theſe words, <hi>Sic olim, modo ſic eſt, ſed monachi faciunt. It wont to be ſo of old, it is not the cuſtome now, the Monkes onlie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it.</hi> The monks ſpeciallie of Sanct <hi>Bennets</hi> order retain the ancient cuſtome. The two thouſand ſouldiers, who were reconciled to the Emperour <hi>Mauritius</hi> about the yere 590. by the travelles of <hi>Gregrorius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euagrius lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and had accepted againe <hi>Philippicus</hi> to be their general captaine, receaved the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon this day ſitting upon the ground. Whereby we may ſee that this cuſtome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to that time among the faithfull, and not among the monkes onlie. Pope <hi>Vrbane</hi> the fourth about the yeere 1264. inſtituted the feaſt of <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> to ſupplie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which had, eſcaped through negligence or humane frailtie in the celebration of the maſſe, and to make amends for anie miſſe: <hi>Quatenus in eo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bulla Vrba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. <hi>4,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod in alijs miſſarum officiis circa ſolennitatem eſt forſitam praetermiſſum, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votâ diligentiâ ſuppleatur, &amp; fideles feſtivitate ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa inſtante intra ſe praeterita memorantes, id quod in ipſis miſſarum ſolenniis, ſecularibus forte agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis impliciti, aut alia ex negligentia, vel fragilitate humana, minus plenè geſſerunt, tunc attentè in humilitate ſpiritus &amp; animi puritate reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi> But as <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> juſtlie taxeth the Pope, the defects, or omiſſions ſhould haue beene ſupplied <hi>ratione a Chriſto praemonſtrata,</hi> by that maner which <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf had ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and not by carying the Sacrament with proceſſion through the ſtreets. It appeareth that the celebration of the Lords ſupper upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18916:6"/> Maundie thurſday after the paterne of the firſt ſupper was appointed for the ſame end, to wit, to ſupply all defectes and omiſſions, which had happened at other times. For the Pope ſayeth, he was moved to chooſe this day for this end ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Maundy thurſday, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that thurſday was ſpent in waſhing of feete, making of Chriſme, and reconciling of peniten s. <hi>In die namque coenae Domini, quo die Chriſtus hoc Sacramentum inſtituit, vniverſalis eccleſiae pro paenitentium reconciliatione, ſacri con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectione chriſmatis, ad impletione mandati circa lotionem pedum, &amp; alijs plurimum occupata ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè vacare non poteſt celebrationi huius maximi ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenti. Chriſts</hi> ordinance behooved to give place to everie toy invented by man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sitting onlie is not ſufficient for anie to communicate with kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elers.</note>The queſtion is now, whether it being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to me to ſitt, I may communicate with others, where ſome do kneele, and al doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ſeverallie, and immediatlie out of the Miniſters hand. It ſeemeth ſtrange to manie, that this ſhould be denied to be lawful. It ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth as ſtrange to me, that it ſhould be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what if all the reſt with whom I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate did kneele, is it enough that I ſitt. Is this the communion of Saincts we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, not to have a regard to the ſtanding, or falling of others, the dignitie, and honour of that action, and the libertie of this reformed Kirk, wherof we ſtand members. I will ſett down the innovations which ar ſenſible to the eyes and eares of everie man, that the anſwer to the queſtion may bee the better underſtood in the particulars, and it may be ſeene where
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18916:6"/> we are either actors, or acceſſory in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating after this manner. Some things I muſt of neceſſitie repeate alreadie treated at length in ſundrie treatiſes both in Engliſh and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, which I will illuſtrate, and whereunto I will adde.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the distributing of the elements.</head>
            <p>THe firſt innovation, is that libertie,<note place="margin">The elements distr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>buted by the Apoſtles among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> is denied to the communicants to divide the elements among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Howbeit it be permitted to us to ſitt. The cuppe after which <hi>Chriſt</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſted he would drinke no more, was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion cuppe, or the laſt paſchall cuppe, which was changed into the Communion cuppe, and conſequentlie one, and the ſame. It was the cuſtome of the Iewes to abſtaine that night from taſting anie thing after the laſt paſchal cuppe. <hi>Christ</hi> alluding to that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome changing this cup, into the euchariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, proteſted he would drinke no more wine in this life. The Evangeliſts <hi>Matthew,</hi> and Mark expreſly ſubjoyne this proteſtation to the communion cuppe. Luke inverteth the order, as the Ieſuites themſelves do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, rendering this reaſon, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of not drinking more might be joyned with the proteſtation of not eating more. Now Chriſt bad the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants divide this cuppe among themſelues.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18916:7"/> And howbeit he had not commanded in expreſſe termes, yet it may be collected of the forme of his ſpeach, when he biddeth them, ſpeaking in the plural number, drink al, of it, and ſayeth not, take thou, drinke thou; as if he had beene delivering it to everie one ſeverally. It was divided among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles by themſelues, reaching it from hand to hand, as the laſt paſchal cuppe, which was changed into this euthariſticall, was carried from hand to hand. <hi>Fuit per proprias Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum manus ab uno ad alium delatus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 861.</note> ſayeth the Ieſuite Swarez. It were ridiculous to ſette downe the cuppe upon the table, that the neareſt might take it up, as I haue ſeene ſome where done. Nay, I ſhould ſay ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, as if the cup were prophaned, if it be reached out of the hand of a lay man (as they call him) but a Chriſtian Brother, as they ſhould call him, &amp; that it were holie to take it from off the table. If we will then divide the cuppe, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles divided it, and ſhewe our ſelues nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ridiculous, nor ſuperſtitious, wee muſt divide it by reaching from hand to hand. The bread is not holyer then the wine, and Chriſt ſaide in the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>Take yee, Eate yee,</hi> as he ſayde, <hi>Drinke yee, Divide yee,</hi> and not take thou, eate thou, as, if hee had been ſpeaking to everie one ſeverally. Therefore right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe Beza,<note place="margin">Beza epist. <hi>12.</hi> Toſſan. in Mat. <hi>26.</hi> Piſc. in Mat. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> Toſſanus, Piſcator, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, gather that Chriſt gaue onely to the neareſt, and they to the nexte and ſo forth.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18916:7"/>
            <p>But yee will ſay,<note place="margin">The objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Christs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon anſwered.</note> the miniſter repreſenteth Chriſts perſon, therefore he ſhould giue the elements out of his owne hands. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not: For as <hi>M. David Lindſay</hi> ſayeth, <hi>He in whoſe name the command is uttered, is properly the giver, and propiner, becauſe by his authoritie it is given, and by the warrant of his word it is received. When the King drinketh to any of his ſubjects,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proceedings at P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie. pag. <hi>60. 61.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and ſends it by the hands of his ſervant, the ſervant is not properly the giver, and propiner, but the deliverer of the gift and propine.</hi> And therefore concludeth, that it may be delivered from hand to hand by the communicants amonge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which could not be, if the former ſequel were good. It is ſaid, Gen. 39. that all that they did, Ioſeph was the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it, becauſe what was done, was done by his appointment. Pilate gaue the bodie of Chriſt, that is, commanded to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Mark. 15.45. Matth. 27.17. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew ſayeth, that Chriſts Diſciples gaue the fiue loues, and two fiſhes to the fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, Matt. 14 19. And yet the Euangeliſt Marke ſayeth 6.41. that Chriſt gaue them to the Diſciples to ſet before them. Chriſt himſelfe, whoſe perſon, yee ſay, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter repreſenteth, when he was preſent in perſon, gaue not to everie one ſeverally, but bade them eate, drink, &amp; divide among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. The Apoſtles at that laſt Supper repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented not Chriſts perſon, for he was there preſent in perſon himſelf, but al faithful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants to the end of the world.<note place="margin">Proceedings pag. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> ſayeth M D. L. <hi>were in that ſupper not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18916:8"/> as diſpenſators of the myſteries of God, but as ghueſts, as the faithfull, as diſciples, and as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants.</hi> But what Chriſt bad his Apoſtles doe as communicants, when he was preſent in perſon, hee biddeth all c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmunicants doe, when there is another to repreſent his perſon. It when there was ſo few communicants, he commanded them to divide, what would he haue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne if he had celebrate to fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand? When miniſters are receivers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mong o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther communicants, they differ nothi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g from other Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in <hi>2</hi> Cor. hom. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nihil differt ſacerdos a ſubito, quando fruendum eſt horrendis myſterijs,</hi> ſayth <hi>Chryſostome.</hi> They are not then miniſters <hi>in actu exercito,</hi> but ſimple communicants. The Deacons about <hi>Iuſtinus Martyrs</hi> time, that is in the next age after the Apoſtles, gaue both the bread and wine to the communicants in the quarters he remained, whereas before the Deacon carried onely the veſſels wherein the elements were contained, as appeareth in the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>turgie aſcribed to S. <hi>Iames.</hi> They uttered no words at the delivery, neither were they yet made halfe Prieſts, as they are now in the Popiſh and Engliſh Church. Now the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons repreſented not Chriſts perſon, but onely the miniſter, or as he calleth him, the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the brethren. It was not then thought neceſſarie that the Paſtor ſhould deliver the elements out of his owne hand, which ought to haue been done, if none but he who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the maſter of the feaſt ſhould deliver. Yea long after <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> time the Deacons diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed the wine. Sometimes the Euchariſt was ſent to the ſick by a Lay man, as we may ſee in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18916:8"/> the hiſtorie of <hi>Serapion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. hist. In. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> The Monks of S. <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> order retaining the ancient forme of cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating upon Thurſday before Eaſter, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate ſitting breaking bread, and reaching the cuppe to other, <hi>Panem azy num frangentes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De origine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum circa coenam. cap.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; calicem in vlcem propinantes, &amp; in totum vele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris coenae veſtigium prae ſe ferentes,</hi> as teſtifieth <hi>Bullinger.</hi> Frier <hi>Rainerius</hi> teſtifieth likewiſe of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> of whom I made mention be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Rainerius in ſumma.</note> that as for the ſacrament of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt <hi>in conventiculis ſuis celebrant, verba illa Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelij recitant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in menſa ſua, ſibique mutuo partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pantes, ſicut in Chriſti coena,</hi> that is, the <hi>Leoniſts</hi> (for ſo he caleth the <hi>Walde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes</hi>) celebrate the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Euchariſt in their conventicles (ſo it pleaſed the Popiſh Frier to call the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the perſecuted) rehearſing the words of the Goſpell at their table, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to other, as was done at Chriſts ſupper. Ye ſee then this ſuperſtition had not ſo farre prevailed, but the Lord had ſome who were not carried away with the ſtream, but kept in the Spoonke in the time of darknes. To ſay that the breaking of the bread is a myſterie, &amp; ought therefore to be performed onely by the miniſter, it followeth not: for the taking, eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drinking of the communicants are myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, that when the Wine is powred into the mouths of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the ſhedding of Chriſts bloud is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Next it is to be conſidered, that fraction or the breaking of the bread is not onely my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, ſignifying the torments and renting of Chriſts body, but alſo ſerveth for diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And becauſe bread was diſtributed by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18916:9"/> breaking, to break in the Scripture ſignifieth to diſtribute by breaking, or to break and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute, when the word <hi>giving</hi> is not added. As Eſay 58.7. <hi>Break thy bread to the hungry,</hi> that is, diſtribute breaking, or break and diſtribute thy bread to the hungry. <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.4. <hi>The lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children asked bread, and there was none to break to them,</hi> that is, to breake and diſtribute to them, or to diſtribute breaking, <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.19. Chriſt ſayth, <hi>When I brake the fiue leaues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the fiue thouſand,</hi> that is, brake and gaue to the diſciples to ſet before the fiue thouſand to be further broken and eaten. Hence it is, that in the Scripture to break is taken for to eate, or to take foode, as <hi>Ierem.</hi> 16. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>Neither ſhall men break bread for them,</hi> that is, they ſhall not celebrate a funerall banquet for them, nor reach unto them the cup of conſola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. And <hi>Act.</hi> 2.46. <hi>They brake bread fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> houſe to houſe,</hi> that is they celebrated love feaſts. But manie interpreters vnderſtand the 42. ver. and Act. 20.7. of the celebration of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And ſo after this figure of ſpeech is meant ſometime, not onlie the act of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, but alſo the end to diſtribute and eate. Siclyke the Apoſtle 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>The bread which we break, is it not the communion of the bodie of Chriſt?</hi> That is, the bread which we breake, diſtribute, and eate, is a ſigne, and ſeale of the communion of Chriſts bodie, as is well obſerved by the interpreters. <hi>Panis quem Frangimus,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. <hi>idem eſt atque inter nos dividimus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſſa in Math. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> The bread which we breake, that is, the bread, which we diuide among us, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Robertus Stephanus. Humbertus</hi> in his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18916:9"/> Book written againſt <hi>Nicetas</hi> a Monke ſayeth, that in the Apoſtles times the faithful brake bread dayly, and had not a perfect maſſe two dayes in the weeke onlie. <hi>Quotidie perſeverantes in templo, &amp; frangentes Panem circa domos. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce verax Evangeliſta teſtatur ſub Apoſtolis fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis quotidie oraſſe, &amp; panem fregiſſe. Et vos, qui estis, qui dicitis duobus tantum diebus hebdoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de miſſam perfectam fieri debere, reliquis imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectam?</hi> I will now retort the objection dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen from the repreſentation of <hi>Chriſts</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Who ever ſaw a great Lord, or King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting inferiors to his table to ſit with him, riſe, and goe alonge to ſerve, and miniſter. <hi>Chriſt</hi> before he ſate downe to ſupper recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending humilitie to his Diſciples aſpiring to preferment, waſhed their feete, but when he came to the table again he ſate among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and kept his place, as maſter of the feaſt: for now they were in the act of feaſting. When the miniſter cometh from his owne place, and goeth along delivering the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, how doth he act in the meane time the perſon of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Maſter of the feaſt. There can be no reaſon for this guiſe, but that the Miniſter muſt breake order, and put off the perſon, which he ſhould act in his owne place, and take vpon him an other office, leaſt the Sacrament ſhould be polluted by the deliverie of the communicants, or as if the cuppe had greater vertue, when <hi>Iohn</hi> who lay in <hi>Chriſts</hi> boſome receaved it out of his hand, then when <hi>Bartholemew</hi> receaved it from <hi>Thomas,</hi> or ſome other. In this order then yee may ſee great miſorder, and groſſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18916:10"/> ſuperſtition. Iuſtlie therefore was that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant woman rebuked by one of the Miniſters of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> not manie yeeres agoe for ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to be neereſt him, at table.</p>
            <p>We have yet farther to conſider, to wit, the end,<note place="margin">The end, and vſe of distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting by the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canst.</note> and uſe of the diſtributing of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants. To drinke of one cuppe repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a communion in one common bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, but not that communication of mutuall dueties of love, and freindſhip, as doth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the cuppe from one to another. The ghueſts of old intertaining others cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſlie at civill banquets reached a cuppe of wine to other, which they called <hi>Phitoteſia,</hi> becauſe it was a ſymbole of love, and freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which name a man may juſtlie impoſe vpon the communion cuppe, ſayeth <hi>Stuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antiqui. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivialium lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> recordeth, that the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants kiſſed one another, when the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was celebrated. <hi>Oſculum pacis porrigere, tempore quo celebrantur Sacramenta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de compunct. cordi,</note> 
               <hi>in vſu eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae eſt:</hi> and to embrace other, <hi>propterea &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterijs, alter alterum amplectitur ut vnam multi fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus. Ierome</hi> making mention of kiſſing, and joyning of hands.<note place="margin">Homil. <hi>51.</hi> ad populum Antioche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> 
               <hi>Quiſquam ne tibi invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus communicat, quiſquamne extenſa manuvertil faciem, &amp; inter ſacras epulas Iudae oſculum por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigit. Paulinus</hi> alſo making mention of joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hands, <hi>Tunc ambo nexi ad invicem dextras damus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Theoph. Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> The kiſſe was the common form of ſalutation among the Orientall people as with vs the ſtriking of hands, or embracing. The men kiſſed the men &amp; women kiſſed others at the communion.<note place="margin">Paul corm ad Cithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am.</note> This kiſſe was leſt of, and in ſtead therof hath ſucceeded the kiſſing of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18916:10"/> the Pax at the maſſe. Seing ſignes &amp; proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of love were thought requiſite at this banquet of love, ought we not to be the more careful to retaine that ſigne which <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath recommended to vs at the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
            <p>Yee are guiltie of this innovation for your part, howbeit it be permitted to you to ſitt.<note place="margin">The commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant guiltie where there is want of the right manner of distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> For yee concurre with your Miniſter as actor to thruſt out this dividing, and diſtributing of the Elements by the communicants, and to bring in miſorder in turning the Miniſter out of his proper place, to vphold ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in deliverie of the Elements out of his owne hands. The reſetter intertaineth the thiefe. The Miniſter giveth, thou receiveſt, and both concurre to ſpoile the Kirk of her liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in this day of controverſie, when ſhe is ſtriving to hold faſt her poſſeſſion. When o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhall be eyther moved by thy example, or forced to quite this libertie, then ſhall the Kirk be ſpoiled of it, and the poſteritie ſhall never recover this libertie againe for anie thing man can ſee. Yee will ſay, your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter will not give it other wiſe, but out of his owne hand. But I ſay againe, that hee would not giue it at all, if hee had not a a receiver. What if hee would not giue it into your hande, but in at the mouth, or clothed it with hoode, and belles, or a ſurplice, ought yee to receave it, and follow your Miniſter, and aſſiſt him to bring in innovations into your particular congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contrarie to the receaved order of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18916:11"/> whole church which yee are bound to defend by your profeſſion, and the confeſſion of our faith.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of confuſion of two Actions in the time of celebration.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Two exerciſes ar confounded in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie by the want of the old forme of distributing.</note>THe ſecond innovation is a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of two actions, and parts of Gods worſhip in one aſſemblie and one time. The Reader is reading, the congregation hearkening to the Reader, or following him in ſinging of Pſalmes in the meane time, when the Miniſter hard beſide is ſpeeking to the communicants, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Elements. If the like were done at the ſolemnization of mariage, it would be thought an intollerable abuſe. Yee will ſay, the people will otherwiſe wearie, and the action become graceleſſe, and cold. It is true, and late experience hath let men ſee this inconvenience. But the right way to amend it, is not to bring in confuſion. For that is to cure a diſeaſe with a remedie worſe then the diſeaſe. Of the two the firſt ſtandeth better with reaſon. For there is no reaſon, that when the Miniſter is ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,<note place="margin">De rebus ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> another voice ſhould be heard in the aſſemblie <hi>Walafridus Strabo</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that of old, the holie Fathers did offer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18916:11"/> and communicate with ſilence, which we yet obſerve vpon the holie Sabboth</hi> (or Saturday) of <hi>Eaſter.</hi> Chanting was brought in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to keepe the people from wearying. So now it is reſtored to the ſame end.</p>
            <p>To returne againe to the right way en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth never in Mens hearts. Forward they will goe, notwithſtanding of anie incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience which rancountereth them, till the angel of the Lord meete them in the way, as he did <hi>Balaam.</hi> The like remedie is uſed in other Kirks, where the want of this manner of diſtribution is, wherunto they never attained. And therefore cannot ſerue for a pretence againſt us, and that comfortable manner of celebration, which we had. Chriſts manner, which we practiſed, needed not ſuch remedies. The hearts of all the hearers were ſtirred up by comfortable exhortation, and ſpeeches of the Miniſter, and together, as it were with one heart, they applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the meditation of that which was ſpoken joyntlie to all, whereas by this deliverie in ſeverall, mens mindes are withdrawen, and loſe that fervencie, and conſtancie in the word of apprehenſion, and meditation, as <hi>Master Fenner</hi> hath well obſerved, in his treatiſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Yee are guilty of this confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. in that yee are partaker in both the actions.</p>
            <p>There is yet further to be conſidered, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18916:12"/> of this confuſion the publike communion is turned into a private.<note place="margin">The publike communion is turned into a private by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding two actions,</note> The exerciſe of the congregation is publike, but the exerciſe of the Miniſter with the communicants is pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate. For it is not ynough to make an action publike to performe it in a publike place, or in ſight of the congregation. If a man kneele down at a pillar to his prayers in ſight of the people, his prayers are never the leſſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate. Yea the congregation is not bound to behold, when they can not heare diſtinctlie, what is ſpoken, but are bound to ſing or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the reader. The miniſter may as wel go to the end of the kirk, as I know ſomewhere is done, or to ſome cloſe Ile, or Conſiſtorie houſe neere by. Yea it were farre more decent then to communicate in the bodie of the Kirk, where the one action can not but diſturbe the other. Ye are not onlie guiltie of the confuſion by partaking in both the actions, but alſo your communicating is onlie a private communicating where there is ſuch confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vtilities of distributing by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants.</note>Put the caſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> had not recommended the diſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we practiſed, but had left it indiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yet ſhould that order of diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting better agree with the general rules, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thing indifferent ought to be ruled, order, decencie, edification, and avoiding of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall. For ſo neither confuſion of exerciſes on the one ſide, nor tediouſnes on the other ſide, nor ſuperſtitious conceits of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters deliverie nor private communions would have pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. It would be a barre alſo to hould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18916:12"/> out kneeling. For religious kneeling in ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and dividing of the elements cannot conſiſt together, where as now by this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating in ſeverall, there reſteth no more, but to perſwade thee, or compel thee to kneel. But ſuppoſe kneeling were never to be feared, yet the abuſes, &amp; corruptions before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are ſufficient matter to moue thee to ſtand to the libertie of this kirk, if thou haue anie ſpoonk of zeale to Gods glorie, to the puritie of his worſhip, and the beautie of his houſe. If any kirk in Europe had enjoyed this precious libertie, as long as we haue done, would they haue quite it ſo eaſilie, as we are like to doe. It is defection in us to deſcend, although not in them who never aſcended to this degree of perfection. The queſtion is not now, whether we ſhall quite the libertie, or quite the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the ſacraments for ever. There is no ſuch tyrannie profeſſed. Quite not a certaine libertie for an uncertaine daunger, doe that which is required on your part, and commit the event to God. The grace of God is not ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſacraments. The Lord promiſed to be a little ſanctuarie to the godly remnant of his people, when they ſhould be ſcattered in other countries, and want the benefit of the temple, and worſhip appropriated to that place. <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 11.16. It is not the wante of the ſacrament, but contempt that maketh a man guiltie, ſayeth <hi>Bernard: Non poteſt autem videri ſacramenta contempſiſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist.</hi> 77.</note> 
               <hi>cui non licet ea ita percipere uti ſunt a Domino conſtituta, &amp; abſit ut ullos neceſſitatis caſus imaginemur, in quibus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat ordinationem Domini violare,</hi> ſayeth <hi>Beza</hi> in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18916:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18916:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18916:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18916:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18916:15"/> his confeſſion: that is, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſaid to haue contemned the ſacraments,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note> to whom it is not permitted to partake them, as they are eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the Lord, &amp; far be it from us to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine anie caſes of neceſſitie, by the which we may violate the Lords ordinance. But what needeth all this feare: for I am ſure, three, or four yeeres abſtinence would conſtrain them to reſtore unto us our libertie again, &amp; to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the communion to be celebrated after the old forme, rather then the people ſhould be defrauded of it. This is the leaſt duty we owe. But we are bound further to defend, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone, if we did profeſſe as we avow in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our faith. The meaneſt profeſſor in the kirk o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scotland is bound to maintain this libertie, &amp; poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion Otherwiſe if he quite, &amp; r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er himſelfe, he is a deſerter of Chriſts cauſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the words uttered at the deliverie of the elements.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta words are not utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uely.</note>THE third innovation is, that the word of promiſe, <hi>This is my bodie, This cup is the new teſtament, &amp;c.</hi> is not uttered demonſtratiuely, when the elements are delivered to everie communicant. It is not enough that the words of the inſtitution were rehearſed before by way of hiſtorie narratiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, or materiallie. This ſacrament is an imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſt not a recitall of his words, &amp; actions, it is to do, as he did, and not to report
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18916:15"/> what he did, ſayth <hi>Pierr du Moulin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 95.</note> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſal doeth no more, but let us ſee what warrant there is to uſe bread, and wine in the celebration of this ſacrament, rather then anie other elements, and to aſſure us that bread, &amp; wine in general are appointed to this uſe. But it can not be ſaid demonſtratiuelie <hi>de individuo ſignato</hi> of this bread, and wine in particular ſet on the table, that it is the bodie and blood of Chriſt. For firſt it muſt be bleſſed, &amp; ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by prayer, and thanksgiving to this uſe, that the miniſter may ſay, <hi>Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that is, this ſanctified bread <hi>is my bodie.</hi> The rehearſal of the word of promiſe euen after the ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſerueth onely for a general warrant. The words then muſt be uttered after the bleſſing demonſtratiuely not to God in a prayer, or forme of oblation, as the popiſh or Engliſh prieſt doeth. For Chriſt uttered them to the diſciples. nor yet by holding, or pointing out the bread to the whole congregation, ſaying <hi>This is my bodie,</hi> as in the baſtarde leiturgies aſcribed to Baſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and Chryſoſtome, where the bread is holden up after the pronouncing of theſe words, &amp; the people anſwer <hi>Amen,</hi> or in the Ethiopian maſſe, where the people anſwer <hi>Amen, Amen, Amen we beleeue it is the bodie of the Lord,</hi> which were ridiculous, &amp; hath ben the original of manie errors. For what if the ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments be not delivered, ſhal they be ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally Chriſts bodie and blood; or the remains? This is a common axiome of the Divines <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta extra uſum non ſunt ſacramenta.</hi> The ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments out of the uſe are nor ſacraments. For howbeit it be not eſſential to bread to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18916:16"/> yet it is eſſentiall to ſacramentall bread to be delivered, taken, and eaten. Chriſt ſaid not, <hi>This is my bodie</hi> to all in generall, &amp; then to everie one in particular take thou, eate thou, as the papiſt and formaliſt doth, but firſt <hi>Take eate,</hi> and then, <hi>This is my bodie,</hi> or <hi>actu con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuo</hi> both bade them take, and eate, and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied what it was he was giving to them. The promiſe is annexed to the commandement, as conditionall. The promiſe hath no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct then if the condition take place. <hi>Si quis ſeparat promiſſionem a mandato diſcedit ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione Chriſti.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Mat. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n aliter igitur habet effectum promiſſio, quam ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> condit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o etiam locum habeat.</hi> ſayth <hi>Robertus Stephanus</hi> It fareth with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall elements, as with pawnes, &amp; pledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in contracts, and bargains. A ring may be appointed for a pledge in matrimonie, yet is it not actually a pledge, without conſent of the other partie, but on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly a meere ring. A ſtone choſen to be a ſigne of a Marche is not actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a marche ſtone, but in the uſe, when it is ſett with conſent of parties in the marche for that end. So the elements are conſecrate, and ſett apart by prayer and thankſgiving, to this uſe, yet are they not actually Chriſts bodie, and blood till they be received and eaten. And therefore a ſacrament properly is defined to be a <hi>ceremonie</hi> or <hi>action.</hi> By a figuratiue kinde of ſpeech the bread may be called the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts bodie, becauſe it is appointed to that ende, as when Iſaack ſaid to Abraham. where is the ſacrifice, that is, the ramm or the lambe appointed for the ſacrifice. But Chriſt called the bread his body not in that ſenſe, but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18916:16"/> in the deliverie and uſe, when it was verilie a ſigne and ſeale of Chriſts bodie. It followeth therefore that the word of promiſe muſt be uttered demonſtratiuely onely in the time of deliverie, receiving, and eating, and to everie one ſeverally, if he will needs giue ſeverally. For otherwiſe he ſhal utter them demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely to ſome, and not to others. The ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall ſignes are like ſeales hanging at the charter. The word of promiſe is the ſpecial, &amp; ſolemn clauſe of the Charter. If at any time it ſhould be uttered, it ſhould be uttered when the ſeale is delivered, ſeeing the ſacramentall words carie the promiſe, &amp; refer the ſignes to their ſacramental uſe. What would we thinke, if the miniſter rehearſed Chriſts command to baptize in name of the father, ſonne, &amp; the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ghoſt, but when he come to the ſprinkling would not ſay, I baptize thee in the name of the father, ſonne, and Holie ghoſt, but utter ſome other words of his owne framing. What is the reaſon the formaliſt wil not utter demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratiuely the words when he delivereth. It is not feare that the kneeler apprehend Chriſts bodie to be under the bread, or the accidents of the bread, for he uttereth them not to the ſitter, more then to him that kneeleth, and is not affraide to conſtraine ignorant people to kneele, although he ſhould conceiue Chriſts bodie to be preſent under the bread, when he hath uttered other words. But here is the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the matter, they place the vertue of conſecration in theſe words, as the Papiſt doth. And therefore becauſe he hath uttered them alreadie, he will not repeate them again;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18916:17"/> leaſt he ſhould ſeem to conſecrate them again. For Mr. <hi>Lindſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>That after the ſacrament is made by the ſacramentall word,</hi> the Paſtor uſeth other words in delivering the elements.<note place="margin">Proceedings pag. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> Mr. <hi>Michelſon</hi> ſayth the like. And yet haue they not uttered theſe words before the delivery, but onely narratiuely, or by way of recitall, which, as I haue ſayd, doth onely ſhew a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in generall. If demonſtratiuely, it muſt be in the time o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prayer, after the Popiſh or Engliſh maner. For they confeſſe they utter them not demonſtratiuely to the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. If conſecration be taken for ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then it is placed in the prayer, or bleſſing. For by prayer, or thankſgiving, the elements are ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied and conſecrated to this uſe. If you will diſtinguiſh betwixt ſanctification &amp; conſecration, as Popiſh Divines doe, then ſay we, that the bleſſing and ſanctifying is but a part, and that conſecration, that is the making of them a ſacrament, conſiſteth in the whole action, as our Divines doe well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue. For except there be receiving, eating &amp; drinking, they are not ſeales of Chriſts body and blood. <hi>Sacramenta perficiuntur uſu.</hi> By the way I obſerue that as the formaliſts utter not Chriſts words demonſtratiuely, ſo agree they not upon a preſcript form of words, but frame them as they pleaſe, whether in form of praier or otherwiſe as they thinke good. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant is acceſſorie to this innovation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee receiveth from him who changeth the words, and giveth the ſeale without the word of promiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18916:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of kneeling in the act of receiving the ſacramentall elements.</head>
            <p>THE fourth innovation is the kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome miniſters, and ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants in the act of receiving. Firſt we are to prove the kneeler guilty. Next, the ſitter communicating with him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not in the ſame degree.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe kneeling were indifferent,<note place="margin">Kneeling in the act of receiuing is idolatrous.</note> yet the kneeler is guiltie of ſcandall: for it is a ſhew of conformitie with the Papiſts in a ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which hath been abuſed by them to the vileſt idolatry that ever was in the world, the worſhip of the bready God, yea invented by the Antichriſt to that end. The formaliſt can not produce one authentick teſtimony for kneeling for a thouſand yeares. The Papiſt is hardened in his ſuperſtition and idolatry, for he thinketh that we are drawing toward him, and that our religion cannot be graced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his rites, or manner of worſhip. The weak brother is offended, &amp; ſtumbleth upon one ſort of idolatry or other. We ſee the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward geſture of an idolater, and who knoweth but their intentions may be bad enough. Yee will ſay the offence is taken, not given. But if it be a thing indifferent, as yee ſay, and not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, but may be omitted, then the offence is given. For you are not ignorant into what evils it may induce the ſimple and ignorant. You ſay the command of the Magiſtrate tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18916:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> away the ſcandall, and that it is better to offend a brother then to offend a Magiſtrate. The word <hi>Offend</hi> is ambiguous. Better it is to offend, that is to diſpleaſe the Magiſtrate, for then I edifie him, vvhereas otherwiſe I ſhould harden him in his courſe, then to offend, that is, lay a ſtumbling block before the poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſoule in the kirk, and ſo deſtroy him for whom Chriſt died. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15. We are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to abſtaine from things in their own nature indifferent, if the vveake brother ſhall offend vvith the uſe of them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15.21. The Magiſtrate hath not power to aboliſh this law. Obedience to the magiſtrate ought not to be the rule of my loue to Gods glory, or ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my brother, vvhich when it is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, Gods glory is trampled under foot. You will ſay, that we are bound to obey the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. It is true, we are bound in conſcience to be ſubject to the magiſtrat, but not to obey him but in the Lord, that is, we are bound to paſſiue obedience, but not to actiue, except in things lawful. A ſcandal is not lawful. Further, know you not that the magiſtrate may abuſe a thing indiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rent, as well as a private man, and make all Iſraell to ſtumble, for he is a ſinfull man Know yee not that it often falleth out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the old ſaying, <hi>Quo volunt Reges, vadun leges,</hi> the lawes muſt ſing as will the King Know yee not that the Magiſtrate may hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his owne private reſpects, and under colour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things indifferent bring in a corrupt religion I need not inſiſt upon this point, it is ſenſibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enough to men of meane iudgment. Say no therefore with <hi>Cain, Am I my brothers keeper</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18916:18"/> The Lord wil ſay to thee, <hi>Thy life for his life</hi> if he be miſſing. 1. <hi>King</hi> 20.39. How careles, alas, are many, although thouſands fall at their right hand, and ten thouſand at their left, ſo that they can either win or retaine the favour of their ſuperiours. But looke how vile the ſoule of thy brother was in thine eyes, thine ſhall be in the eyes of God, except thou repent and amend.</p>
            <p>I am now to proue it idolatrous,<note place="margin">Kneeling in the act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving is I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous.</note> firſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the publick intent of our ſuperiours: Next, ſimply, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſoever intent men can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. That we may know what is the publick intent, we are to conſider the intent of the Engliſh Church: for conformitie with that Church is intended. Next, the act of Perth Aſſembly which is urged.</p>
            <p>The kirke of England intendeth kneeling for reverence of the ſacrament:<note place="margin">The publick intent of the Engliſh Kirk is idolatrous.</note> for in the booke of common prayer, whereunto they are bound by the ſtatute, 1 <hi>Elizab.</hi> kneeling is enioyned upon this ground, That the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might not be prophaned, but held in a reverent and holy eſtimation. D. <hi>Morton</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, <hi>Are yee then of opinion, either that the ſacrament cannot be prophaned, or that the Church had not reaſon to prevent, or avoid the prophanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this ſacrament of the Eucharist.</hi> And again, to ſtop the mouths of blaſphemous papiſts vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifying our ſacrament with the ignominious names of Bakers bread, Vintners wine, profane elements. Ale-cakes, and ſuch like reprochfull termes, <hi>did hold it fit that wee by our outward reverence in the manner of receiving the Euchariſt, might teſtifie our due eſtimation of ſuch holy rites,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18916:19"/> which are conſecrated to ſo bleſſed an uſe, as is the communion of the body and blood of Chriſt, and that thereby we might repell the ſtaine and ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie which ſuch virulent and unhallowed tongues did caſt upon them.</hi> The Replyer to Doctor <hi>Morton</hi> refelleth this allegeance of ſtopping the mouthes of Papiſts,<note place="margin">Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly <hi>2.</hi> part. pag. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> and telleth us, that ſome cloſe diſſembling adverſaries did hinder the worke of reformation ſo much as they could, and that they haue done ſo ever ſince, and doe ſo ſtill to this day. Howſoever it is, yee ſee they kneele to teſtifie their due eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy rites. Mr. <hi>Hatton</hi> ſaith, they kneele to put a difference between the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie bread and wine, and theſe ſacramental, to which they giue the more reverence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is more then ordinary bread and wine.<note place="margin">Book <hi>2.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nst the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iniſters of Cornwall &amp; Devonſhire.</note> What can be ſayd more plainly. Maſter <hi>Rogers</hi> in his ſecond Dialogue hath ſome words to the ſame effect. Now to kneele for reverence of the elements, becauſe they are more then ordinarie bread and wine, or to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie our due eſtimation of the holy rites, which are imployed about the elements, is I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The publick i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tent of our Church is idolatrous.</note>We are next to try the publick intent by the act of Perth Aſſembly ratified in Parliament, the tenor whereof followeth, as it is publiſhed after fining and refining.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The act of Perth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt kneeling.</note>
               <hi>Since we are commanded by God himſelfe, that when we come to worſhip him, wee fall downe and kneele before the Lord our Maker, and conſidering withall, that there is no part of divine worſhip more heavenly and ſpirituall, then is the holy receiving of the bleſsed body and blood of our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18916:19"/> Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt. Like as the moſt humble and reverent geſture of the body in our meditation and lifting up of our hearts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh well ſo divine and ſacred an action, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore notwithſtanding our Church hath uſed ſince the reformation here, to celebrate the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to the people ſitting, by reaſon of the great abuſe uſed in the Idolatrous worſhip of Papists, Yet now, ſince all memorie of bypaſt ſuperſtition is blotted out of the hearts of the people, prayſed be God, in reverence of God, and in due regard of ſo divine a myſterie, and in remembrance of ſo myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call an union, as we are made partakers of thereby, the aſsemblie thinketh good, that the bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be celebrated hereafter to the people humblie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The falſe &amp; ſuperfluous clauſes of the act.</note> 
               <hi>and reverently kneeling upon their knees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue here two lyes encloſed in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis. It is untrue, that al memorie of by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt paſt ſuperſtition is blotted out of the hearts of the people, as the countrie wel knoweth, &amp; the behaviour of ſome ignorant people, when they were kneeling, hath alreadie bewrayed. Next it is untrue, that the abuſe in time of papiſtrie was the onely and principal cauſe of reſtoring the geſture of ſitting at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of reformation. If they had aimed only at the reformation of that abuſe, they needed not to haue reſtored ſitting, ſtanding or tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>en paſſant</hi> would haue ſerved the turne. Both ſitting, and diſtributing of the elements by the communicants were reſtored at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, becauſe moſt agreeable, and neare to the pattern of the firſt ſupper.</p>
            <p>We haue three reaſons in this act, wherefore we ſhold kneel, as M. <hi>Lindſay</hi> hath analyzed it.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:18916:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The first rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the act refuted.</note>The firſt reaſon in the narratiue is this, <hi>Since we are commanded by God himſelfe, that when wee come to worſhip him, we fal down and kneel before the Lord our maker.</hi> Relatiue to this in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion we haue theſe words. <hi>Therefore in reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God, the aſsemblie thinketh good that this ſacrament be celebrated to the people kneeling upon their knees.</hi> For the confirmation of this reaſon is alledged th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pſalm verſe 7. By this rude reaſon it is a ſin not to kneele in the act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, &amp; al who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed their example ſince, haue ſinned. For if we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by God, it is a ſin to violate his commandement. Next the word <hi>worſhip</hi> is not taken here for anie kinde of religious, and divine ſervice, or action expreſſed by the word <hi>Cultus</hi> in latine, but more ſtrictly for adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or rather that geſture of proſtrating the whole body. The people of God uſed four ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of the bodie, as ſignes of honour: firſt a bending or bowing down of the head, which they expreſſed by the word <hi>Cadad,</hi> this was the leaſt degree. Next a bending or bowing of the ſuperiour bulke of the body, which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the word <hi>Carang.</hi> The third kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which they expreſſed by the word <hi>Barach.</hi> The fourth falling down proſtrate with their hands &amp; feet ſpread, which they expreſſed by the word <hi>Histachaveh.</hi> The laſt three are all mentioned in the 6 verſe of the 95 Pſalme. If there were any command here included to fal down, when we receiue the ſacrament, we ſhould be commanded not onely to bowe the ſuperior bulke of the bodie, as Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> commanded to be done at the elevation, or to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18916:20"/> kneele, as we are now commanded to doe, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo to proſtrate our ſelues upon our face, with our hands and feet ſpread, for ſo do ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the manner. But there is here onely an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nvitation and exhortation, not a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not to kneel, when they come before the Lord to worſhip, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me before the Lord, that is before the arke, which is called the face of God, and worſhip, that is proſtrate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, kneele, and bow themſelues before the Lord their maker in token of thankſgiving. It is great ignorance to infer hereupon, that we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to kneel in the act of receiuing the ſacramental elements in the act of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hearing the word, which are al acts of divine ſervice, or worſhip in a larger ſence. The words relatiue in the concluſion taken ſimplie are not true. For we are not bound at al times to kneel in reverence of God. For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue precepts bindeth us ever, but not to practiſe at everie time. For then we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be off our knees, becauſe we ought ever to carie with us reverence to God.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon in the narratiue of the act is this, <hi>And conſidering with al,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond reaſon in the act for kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refuted.</note> 
               <hi>that there is no part of divine worſhip more heauenly and ſpirituall, then is the holy receiuing of the bleſſed bodie and blood of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to this reaſon we haue in the concluſion theſe words: <hi>And in regarde of ſo divine a myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the aſſemblie thinketh good, that that bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament be celebrated to the people humblie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently, kneeling upon their knees.</hi> Myſtery (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he) is not taken here for the elements, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not ſaid <hi>Mysteries,</hi> but <hi>Myſterie,</hi> and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18916:21"/> by <hi>Myſterie</hi> is meant the holy receiving of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> body and blood of Chriſt, which is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the narratiue. When the acte was firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> formed, the copies that we ſaw, had the word <hi>Myſteries.</hi> It is now refined, and yet they are not a whit farther off. For what reaſon is there to refer it to the remoter words of the narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, when i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be referred to the nearer words of the cocluſion, to wit the <hi>celebration of the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion,</hi> &amp; the words following, <hi>that bleſſed ſacrament.</hi> But the truth is, it is relatiue to al the three, as we ſhal make evident in the owne place. But admit his interpretation. If we ſhould kneel, when we receiue Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood in regard of ſo divine a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, then ſhould we doe it whenſoever we eate Chriſts fleſh, and drinke his bood. But ſo it is, that as oft, as the promiſes of the goſpell are read, exponed, or in anie part of the ſermon rehearſed, and the hearer beleeueth, he receiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and eateth Chriſts fleſh, and drinketh his blood. But then we muſt be attentiue hearers, and not ſpeake to God, when God is ſpeaking to us. Attentiue hearing, and the work of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending, conſidering, diſcerning, trying what is ſpoken, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not conſiſt with preſenting our prayers upon our knees. Neither is knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling urged in this part of divine ſervice. It is not then ſimplie in due teg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd of ſo divine a myſterie, as is the receiving of Chriſts body and blood, that kneeling is intended (for the ſpirituall, and inward receiuing is common both to the word and ſacraments) but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſo divine a myſterie, as is the receiuing of Chriſts body and blood in the ſacrament,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18916:21"/> or which is all one, in regard of the myſticall or ſacramentall manner of receiving, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently in regard of the ſymbols or ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical rites employed about the ſymbols. It is cleare then, that in the narratiue of the act, by the receiving of the body and blood of Chriſt, is meant a ſacramentall receiuing, and to that manner of receiuing is the word <hi>Myſterie</hi> relatiue in the concluſion.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon, ſayeth he,<note place="margin">The third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the act for kneeling refuted.</note> is the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie betweene the outward geſture of our body, and the meditation and lifting up of our hearts, when we remember, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the myſtical union betwixt Chriſt and us, and among our ſelues, whereof we are made partakers by the receiuing of Chriſts bleſſed body and blood. This reaſon depending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former ſhall receiue the like anſwer. Are we not made partakers of that myſticall union, when at the hearing of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Goſpell, we eate Chriſts fleſh and drinke his blood? Many haue been partakers of this myſticall union, who were never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of this ſacrament.</p>
            <p>But the words of the narratiue,<note place="margin">The right meaning of the third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion cannot ſorte together after that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Therefore he ſhunneth to ſet down the words of the narratiue, and of the concluſion relatiue to them. For in the narratiue is no mention made of the myſticall union, neither is it ſaid in the narratiue, <hi>that the moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and reverent geſture of the bodie well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth our meditation, and the lifting upp of our hearts, when we conſider the mysticall union betwixte Chriſt and us:</hi> but that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18916:22"/> 
               <hi>the moſt humble and reverent geſture of our b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in our meditation, and lifting up of our hearts becommeth wel ſo divine and ſacred an action as is the receiving of the body and blood of Chriſt.</hi> Now this reaſon receiueth the like anſwer that the two former. For it may be aſked, why becommeth that humble geſture of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and lifting up of our hearts, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of Chriſts body and blood, in the act of rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iving the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cramentall elements, more then in the hearing of the promiſes of the goſpell, if it were not in regard of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall elements. Next, what h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mble geſture is that, which is ſo ſuteable with m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ditation. Men doe meditate walking, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting, lying, but not kneeling. For by me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tation a man doth ſpeak to himſelf, holding a ſoliloqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in his own ſoule. Againe what humble geſture is that, which beſt becommeth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lifting up of the heart, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing the heart may be lifted up without prayer, and in prayer kneeling doeth ſignifie rather the ſubmiſſion and humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then the lifting up of the heart. The lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the eyes or hands are the outward ſignes of lifting up of the heart.</p>
            <p>In the concluſion, the words which he maketh relatiue to the former are theſe:<note place="margin">To remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is not to lift up the heart by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> 
               <hi>In remembrance of ſo mysticall an union, as we are made partakers of by ſo divine a myſterie. In remembrance,</hi> that is, in memorie: for ſo runne the words, <hi>In reverence, in due regard in remembrance.</hi> But leaſt I ſhould ſeeme to cavill at words, let it be <hi>in remembring.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there be any force in this reaſon, we ſhould kneele, whenſoever we remember ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18916:22"/> myſticall an union. If this clauſe in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion were relatiue to the former in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue, then by lifting up of the heart is not meant prayer. For to remember, or as he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, to co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſider is not to pray. Howbeit there by pondering, remembring, conſidering, and momentanie meditations, are ejaculations of meditation in prayer, as there are momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie petitions, and ejaculations of prayer, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to our meditations, yet to pray is not to meditate, nor to meditate to pray, nor n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man of ſound judgment ever defined them ſo, but are two diverſe exerciſes of the ſoule, and require divers employments of the bodie, divers times, and divers denomination<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the principall worke, and not from the inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ejaculations. So that by the lifting up of the heart can not be meant prayer. For one humble geſture of kneeling is not ſutable both to meditation and prayer, both to ſpeaking unto God, and to our ſelues.</p>
            <p>We are not directed by the act to meditate,<note place="margin">We are not directed by the act to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, or pray in the acte of receiving.</note> and lift up our hearts, when we remember, and conſider this myſticall union, whereof we are made partakers by receiving Chriſts body and blood, but only to uſe that humble ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture when we receiue Chriſts bodie and blood, which we uſe in our meditation, and lifting up of our hearte, although we be not then meditating, or lifting up our heart. But put the caſe, that we be ſo directed, and that by <hi>lifting up of the heart</hi> be meant prayer, yet it muſt be meant a mentall prayer, not a vocall: for that is a lifting upp of the voice. The mental prayer muſt either follow
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18916:23"/> the vocall prayer of the Miniſter, or muſt be conceaved by the kneeler.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mentall pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er following the vocall of the Minister in the act of receaving was not enjoyned.</note>The Lords, over-rulers of that aſſembly meant not a mental prayer following the vocal pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Miniſter. For then they would have ordained ſome prayer to be vttered by the Miniſter, or els that every Miniſter ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave a prayer as he thought good. But no ſuch thing was done. Some, who are ſaid to have beene penners of the act themſelves, vſe not a forme of prayer at the deliverie of the Elements, nor yet anie other, ſo farre as I know. Everie man was left to his owne free choiſe of words, whether in form of prayer, or otherwiſe. Kneeling therfore ſhould not be vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged til in another like aſſembly they have dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the appurtenances. They were ſo glad of kneeling, that they forgot all the requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, and ſo they brought forth a ſhapeleſſe birth, like the beares whelpe, which wanteth eyes, and is a rude deformed lumpe when it is brought forth, and muſt be cheriſhed, and licked a long time before it be brought to a perfect forme. But ſuppone that a vocall prayer had beene ordained, yet is not knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling enjoyned in regard of anie vocall prayer. For the communicant kneeleth both before, and after the receaving, and the Miniſter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth if he follow the Engliſh forme, his wiſh, or requeſt of three or foure words, a ſhort ejaculation of the tongue ſooner then the communicant can addreſſe himſelfs to his knees, and before he eate, the other endeth his prayer, biddeth him eate, and be thankful, which is an admonition, or exhortation, not a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18916:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> prayer, and ſo leaveth him, and goeth to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. Next, if kneeling were intended in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of anie vocal prayer of the Miniſter, then where there is no vocall prayer at the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, kneeling is not intended, and they have greatlie failed, who have kneeled. But that is done almoſt everie where, where there is kneeling. Thirdlie, if in regard of the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prayer of the Miniſter, then if a Miniſter vtter demonſtrativelie Chriſts owne words, the communicant muſt not kneele, but if h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vtter the words of mans framing he muſt kneele. So Chriſts order muſt be overthrown that kneeling may have place. Fourthlie ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vocall prayer had beene enjoyned, and the communicant to follow it mentallie, what can be the reaſon to vrge kneeling in regard of that vocal prayer, rather then anie other, if there were no further intended, then to kneele in regard of the vocall prayer of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. At a convention holden at Sainct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes before Perth aſſemblie, it was thought good that people ſhould either ſtand or kneele in time of prayer, at other times. What need I inſiſt vpon this point, ſeing there was no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for a vocall prayer, farre leſſe a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that kneeling was intended in regard of that prayer.<note place="margin">The mentall prayer of the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants owne framing not enjoyned not kneeling in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of it.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If by lifting vp of the heart</hi> could be meant the mentall prayer of the communcants owne framing, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiving, it muſt be either a ſet &amp; continued prayer, or ſhort ejaculation &amp; momentanie petitions. The ſet and continued prayer, which may be called <hi>Oratio inſtructa,</hi> a prayer ſet in order according to <hi>Davids
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18916:24"/> phraſe Pſal.</hi> 5. <hi>Mane inſtrua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coram te, &amp; ſum ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiturus,</hi> cannot conſiſt with the exerciſe of receaving, eating, drincking, and the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall actions anſwering analogicallie to them. Eyther the minde muſt be abſtracted from meditation, and conſideration of theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word rites, whereabout the ſenſes, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are employed, or els it muſt be diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and divided betwixt two exerciſes. A Prince would not be content to be ſo vſed by a poore ſupplicant, to ſee him employed in another action, athough lawful and honeſt, when he is preferring his petition to him.<note place="margin">Dist. <hi>49.</hi> cap. ſacer.</note> It is then the ſacrifice of fooles. <hi>Offer it now to thy Governor, wil he be pleaſed with thee, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thy perſon Malach.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Indignum eſt dare Deo, quod dedignaretur homo.</hi> If we make petition but to ſome earthlie Prince we fixe the eye both of bodie, and minde up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n him, and ſcare leaſt ſome incongruous, or vnſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie word move him to aver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his countenance. <hi>Tot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m in cum menti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; corporis aciem defigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; de nutu ej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ida expectatione pende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llat.</hi> 23. <hi>cap.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>non mediocrit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntes, ne quod forte incongruum verbum audientes miſericordiam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertat</hi> ſayeth <hi>Caſſianus.</hi> The like incongruity of confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding two exerciſes receaving, eating, drinking in time of ſett prayer, and adoration vpon our knees was never heard among the verie barbarians, and I thinke would never have beene heard among Chriſtans, if they had not imagined falſly that they were eating the fleſh, and drinking the blood of their God. Next, if by <hi>lifting vp of the heart</hi> be meant the ſett mentall prayer of the communicant,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18916:24"/> it will follow, that kneeling cannot be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vrged, then the ſett mentall prayer it ſelf. But I beleeve that the communicant, if he be well exerciſed in the mentall actions, anſwering analogicallie to the outward, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth worthilie, howbeit he conceave not a ſet mental prayer. Thirdlie if kneeling be enjoyned in regard of ſett mentall prayer to be conceaved by the communicant, then a ſecret, or private prayer is commanded in a publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k aſſemblie, without a vocall, either of the Miniſter, or of him that prayeth, even then, when the Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, and congregation is not praying. He concurreth not with the congregation, nor the congregation with him. And beſide, the ſignes, and geſtures of ſecret, and mentall prayer, where there is not vocall, ſhould be concealed in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, far leſſe ſhould they be extorted.</p>
            <p>They may as well enjoyn the communicant to lift up his eyes or knock on his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, that we may know he is praying, as to enjoyne kneeling, if it were intended in regard of this ſecret prayer. For kneeling, lifting up of the hands, eyes, knocking on the breaſt, are naturall adumbrations of the inward motions, and paſſions of our ſoule, which ought not to be extorted. It muſt be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for ſome other regard, that knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is intended, then in regard of anie ſett mentall prayer. For whether he pray, or not, mentallie, he is urged to kneele.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18916:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18916:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18916:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18916:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18916:27"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Kneeling not intended in regard of the eiaculations of the heart.</note>If by <hi>lifting up of the heart</hi> be meant the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentanie petitions, and ſhort ejaculations of the ſoule, that lifting up may very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with ſet meditation, and not onely with this action of receiving, eating, drinking the ſacramentall elements, but alſo with the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of our ordinary and daily foode, eating and drinking at common tables. In a word, with all our actions whether civil or religious, and may be incident to my paſſing by a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixe, at which time I may not kneele, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I deteſt the Image. I may very well paſſing by with neglect or contempt, groane to God for the blindneſſe of the people, or lift up my hand, or my eyes, becauſe theſe geſtures may well expreſſe our inward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaculations. But kneeling attendeth not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ejaculations, but upon ſet prayer, or thankeſgiving purpoſely intended. It was therefore a ſilly tale of one of our miniſters, to ſay that wee granted they might lift up their eyes, but we envied the poore knee. Will any man inferre, that I may kneele at eating of daily food, becauſe I may then lift up my eyes? Theſe ejaculations, and holy motions of the heart may be, and are often incident at hearing of the word, and ſometimes more fervent then at the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Sacrament It is not therefore in regard of that lifting uppe of the heart by ſhort eiacalations of prayer that knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is intended.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18916:27"/>
            <p>What hath beene ſayd againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of prayer,<note place="margin">The pretence of mentall &amp; reall thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giving an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> let it be applyed to thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving vocall, or mentall, ſet, and contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or iaculatorie, and momentanie. If they will ſay, that the action of eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is a reall thankeſgiving, and ſhewing forth of the Lords death, the Apoſtle ſayth not ſo, but requireth a declaration by words of the Lords death as oft as we communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate. But put the caſe the Apoſtle had ſayd, by eating and drinking yee ſhewe forth the Lords death, yet is not the action a reall thankſgiving, but a reall commemoration to ſpeake ſo, of Chriſts death and paſſion, and conſequentlie of the nature of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſhewing forth of the Lords death and paſſion, and not of the nature of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving. It is one thing to profeſſe and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Gods mercies before men for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of man, and another thing to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up thankes to God by way of adoration. God may be honoured many wayes, but every honour is not adoration. Praiſe and thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving differ. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homil.</hi> 26. <hi>Tom.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Christum praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari per linguam, per epistolam, per ſacramentum corporis &amp; ſanguinis ejus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having examined all the reaſons of the Act according to Maiſter <hi>Lindſayes</hi> owne interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,<note place="margin">A queſtion to diſcover the nakedneſſe of the Act.</note> that the Reader may the better conceiue how rude they are, I propone this queſtion. Seeing vvee receiue the ſame benefite invvardlie and ſeverallie, vvee eate the fleſh, and drinke the blood of Chriſt as oft as wee beleeue the promiſes of the Goſpell read, exponed, or in any part of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18916:28"/> ſermon rehearſed, and may haue the heart then lifted up, yea ſometimes more fervent motions then when we receiue the ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall elements of bread and wine; Why are we enioyned to kneele at the one time more then at the other, if it be not in regard of the outward ſignes and rites, which is idolatry? Nay, I ſhould urge further. Seeing there was onely a voyce at the delivery of the word, and here is a viſible obiect ſet before the eye, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it were urged there, wherefore ſhould it bee urged here? <hi>Yee heard the voyce of the words, but ſaw no ſimilitude, onely yee heard a voyce.</hi> Deut. 4.12. According to his private interpretation I forme another act <hi>mutatis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis</hi> like the act of Perth, that it may be the better underſtood.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Another act f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmed to diſcover the mystery and meaning of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct of Perth.</note>
               <hi>SInce we are commanded by God himſelfe, that when we come to worſhip him, we fall downe and kneele before the Lord our maker, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering withall, that there is no part of divine worſhip more heavenly and ſpirituall, then is the holy receiving of the bleſſed body and blood of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt. Like as the moſt humble and reverent geſture of the body in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, and lifting up of our hearts, becommeth well ſo divine and ſacred an action. Therefore not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our Church hath uſed, ſince the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of religion here, to heare the promiſes of the Goſpell read, exponed, or in any part of the ſermon rehearſed ſitting, by reaſon of ſome great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe in former times; yet now, ſeeing all memory of by-paſt abuſe is blotted out of the hearts of the people, praiſed be God, in reverence of God, and in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18916:28"/> due regard of ſo divine a myſterie, and in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſo myſticall an union. as wee are made partakers of thereby, the Aſſembly thinketh good, that the promiſes of the Goſpell being read, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or rehearſed in any part of the Sermon, that the people hearken reverently kneeling upon their knees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there any reaſon in the act of Perth, which may not ſort with this?<note place="margin">Three or foure phraſes in the Act ſignifying one thing.</note> May not the reader here perceiue, that by <hi>receiving of the body and bloud of Chriſt</hi> in the narratiue, is meant a myſticall receiving of the ſacrament, and relatiue to this phraſe in the concluſion are theſe three following, <hi>the holy communion, divine myſterie, &amp; bleſſed ſacrament,</hi> ſo that al the foure ſignifie one thing, and without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie to other, they cannot cohere in any tollerable conſtruction of words. Let the act then bee formed, as it ſhould runne in right conſtruction in maner following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SInce we are commanded by God himſelfe, that when we come to worſhip him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Act rightly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> 
               <hi>we fall downe and kneele before the Lord our maker, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering withall, that there is no part of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip more heavenly and ſpirituall, then is the holy receiving of the body and blood of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt. Like as the moſt humble and reverent geſture of the body in our meditation, and lifting up of our hearts becommeth well ſo divine and ſacred an action. Therefore notwithſtanding our Church hath uſed, ſince the reformation of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion here, to receiue the body and blood of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt ſitting, by reaſon of the great abuſe uſed in the idolatrous worſhip of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18916:29"/> Papiſts, yet now ſince all memory of by-paſt ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition is blotted out of the hearts of the people, praiſed be God: in reverence of God, and due regard of ſo divine a myſterie, and in remembrance of ſo myſticall an union as wee are made partakers of thereby, the Aſſembly thinketh good that the people receiue the body and blood of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt humbly and reverently kneeling upon their knees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">By the word Mysterie is meant the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, or ſacramentall receiving.</note>May not any man here ſee evidently, that by <hi>Divine Myſtery</hi> is meant the receiving of the body and blood of Chriſt in the myſterie of the Supper, or the myſticall and ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall receiving which ſtandeth in ſignes &amp; rites, wherein it differeth from the ſpirituall. By the word <hi>Myſtery</hi> in the ſingular number, as well as by the word <hi>Myſteries</hi> in the plurall number, is meant the ſacrament very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently among the ancient Writers. <hi>Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius Areopagita</hi> entituleth the chapter of the Lords Supper,<note place="margin">De eccleſ. Hierarch.</note> 
               <hi>The myſtery of the Synaxis or holy communion. Ambroſe</hi> ſayth, <hi>Indignus eſt Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, qui aliter myſterium celebrat, quàm ab eo traditum est,</hi> that he is unworthy in the Lords account who celebrateth the myſtery other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then hee hath delivered it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11</note> 
               <hi>Oecamenius</hi> ſaith, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our maſter the Lords Supper.<note place="margin">Hieron. in Pſal. <hi>47.7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ierome</hi> ſayth, <hi>Licet in myſterio poſſit intelligi, tamen ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riùs corpus Chriſti, &amp; ſanguis eius ſermo ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum eſt,</hi> that howbeit it may be underſtood of the myſtery, that yet more truly the words of the Scripture may bee called the body and blood of Chriſt. What need many teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies?<note place="margin">Exercit. pag. <hi>550.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caſaubone</hi> ſayth of this ſacrament,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18916:29"/> 
               <hi>Dicitur etiam antonomaſticè to myſterion, aut numero multitudinis ta myſteria.</hi> In the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh confeſſion the bread, and wine are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>The holie, and heavenlie myſteries of the bodie, and blood of Chriſt.</hi> In the ſervice booke the word <hi>Myſterie</hi> is vſed in the ſingular number. <hi>Maſter Lindſay</hi> himſelf vſeth ſome time the word <hi>Myſterie,</hi> and ſometime the word <hi>Myſteries</hi> in his Reſolutions. The word <hi>Myſterie</hi> is often vſed in the ſingular number becauſe both the ſignes, and the rites em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about them are referred to one Chriſt ſignified.</p>
            <p>This act may paſſe among both Papiſts and Lutherans,<note place="margin">The act of Perth may paſſe among Lutherans &amp; Papists.</note> this clauſe <hi>(Notwithſtanding our Church hath vſed, ſince the Reformation here, to celebrate the holie communion to the people ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, by reaſon of the great abuſe vſed in the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous worſhip of Papiſts, yet now ſince all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of by-paſt ſuperſtition is blotted out of the hearts of the people praiſed be God)</hi> being blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out, as juſtlie it ought: for it is falſe, as I have alreadie ſaid. It is ſuperfluous. For the act is whole, and entire without it, the concluſion anſwering to the narrative. And it is inſert for a mocke. For immediatlie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and before they condemne our Church for want of reverence and due regard to this Sacrament, which ought to have prevailed above all other reſpects, if their reaſon were forcible. This falſe, ſuperfluous, and mocking clauſe being blotted out, yee have the whole act, as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:18916:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SInce we are commanded by God himſelfe, that when we come to worſhip him,<note place="margin">The Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran or popiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> we fall downe and kneele before the Lord our maker, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering withall, that there is no part of divine worſhip more heavenly and ſpirituall, then is the holy receiving of the bleſſed body and blood of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt. Like as the moſt humble and reverent geſture of the body in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, and lifting up of our hearts, becommeth well ſo divine and ſacred an action. Therefore in reverence of God, and due regard of ſo divine a myſterie, and in remembrance of ſo myſticall an union, as wee are made partakers of thereby, the Aſſembly thinketh good, that bleſſed ſacrament be celebrated to the people humbly and reverently upon their knees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This act I ſay may paſſe among Papiſts, and Lutherans.<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>doration, or ells reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct.</note> For they maintaine that all the communicants, even the verie wicked, and hypocrits receave the verie bodie, and blood of Chriſt in at their mouth, the Papiſt vnder the accidents of bread, and wine, the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran vnder or within the elements of bread, and wine. For the Papiſt and Lutherane hath beſide the ſpirituall receaving, which they grant onlie to the godlie, a Sacramentall but eſſentiall, and reall receaving of the verie bodie, and blood of Chriſt in at the mouth, which they grant alſo to the wicked. The act of the communicants receaving is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe expreſſed here, then by the recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the bodie and blood of Chriſt. May wee not therefore juſtlie ſuſpect the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall reall receaving of Chriſts bodie, and blood to have been intended by the firſt pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18916:30"/> of the act, whereſoever it was firſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſeing there is nothing contrarie to this meaning in the act, it is damned as curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie to enquire after what manner Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament of the ſupper. Yea it is plainlie avouched that Chriſts blood is after a more ſublime manner preſent in the Sacramentall wine, then it is in the water of Baptiſme. So in this ſenſe to kneele in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the divine myſterie is to kneele in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Chriſts bodie reallie preſent, and the ſignes together, conjunctlie as the totall object of adoration, and ſo the ſignes ſhal be worſhiped by way of coadoration. So the Papiſts worſhip the bodie of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or accidents togither. <hi>Non ſolum Chriſtus ſub ſpeciebus existens, ſed etiam to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sacramentum viſibile, vt ex Christo &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciebus constat vnico latriae actu adorandum eſt,</hi> ſayeth <hi>Swarez.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>diſp.</hi> 65. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſimpliciter hoc Sacramentum adorandum eſſe adoratione latriae ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluta, &amp; perfecta, qua per ſe adoretur Chriſtus. coadorentur autem ſpecies, quia hoc Sacramentum in re eſt vnum Conſtans ex Chriſto &amp; ſpeciebus.</hi> If no man can be perſwaded that there is anie ſuch intent, yet the other reſpect is at leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, to wit, to kneel in regard of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that is, of the myſtical rites, and elements, which is Idolatrie. For to kneele in regard of the elements, is to adore them. Becauſe kneeling in Religious vſe is ever a geſture of adoration, and ſoveraine worſhip, which belongeth onlie to God, and by it is deſigned ſome times the whole worſhip of God. <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam proſkuneſm, quae hominibus propter analogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18916:31"/> cum Deo ſimilitudinem legitimè tribuitur, ita Deo propriam cenſeo, cum Religioſa eſt, ut totus cultus divinus illa ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſignetur, Chriſtus illam Diabolo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>put. pag. <hi>233.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; Angelus ſibi abjudicet, hoc argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to quod Dei propria ſit,</hi> ſayeth <hi>Arminius.</hi> Yet I cannot ſee how the word <hi>Mystery</hi> can be other wiſe taken in the act, then for the receaving of the ſignes, and the thing ſignified together Sacramentallie. It is true God offereth the thing ſignified as oft as the outward ſignes are preſented vnto us, but the fail is vpon the part of the receaver, who wanteth faith and recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth onely the outward ſignes.</p>
            <p>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e have examined the publick intent, which wee find to be idolatrous.<note place="margin">The private intents of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municants examined.</note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoever be the privat intent of the communicant he muſt be interpreted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the publik intent. Otherwiſe a man may goe to Rome, and kneele. But we will exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine alſo what the communicant can alledge for his private intent. The pretence of men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall prayer, or thankſgiving we have alreadie diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The pretence of receauing a precious gift, the body and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood of Christ.</note>Firſt yee ſay, ye are receaving a precious gift, the bodie, and blood of Chriſt. Will not anie man doe reverence to the king, when he receaveth a gift out of his hand? This pretence hath beene alreadie anſwered. For we receave the ſame benefite at the hearing of the word. But farther it may be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whether thou be receaving ſuch a gift, howbeit God be offering it. Next the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the offer is to be conſidered, to wit, not immediatlie, but mediatlie by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie of the word, and Sacraments. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18916:31"/> we muſt not imagine that Chriſts bodie is offered vnto us in the Sacrament, as if we had never receaved his bodie before. Did we not receave his bodie at the Sacrament in former times, did we receave, and then looſe againe? Yea we receave the bodie of Chriſt at our firſt converſion, we receave his fleſh, and blood in the word, before we receve them in the Sacrament. We are in Chriſts bodie before we eate of Chriſts bodie,<note place="margin">De civit. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> ſayeth <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine. Dicendum non eſt eum comedere corpus Chriſti, qui non eſt in corpore Chriſti.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſayeth, that we are made partakers of Chriſts bodie in Baptiſme. <hi>Nulli aliquate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt dubitandum, vnumquemque fidelium cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris, &amp; ſanguinis tunc eſſe participem, quando in Baptiſmate membrum efficitur Chriſti.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſayeth. <hi>By one ſpirit we are all Baptized into one bodie.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. <hi>That we are graffed in Chriſt, that we putt on Chriſt. Rom.</hi> 6.35. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.27.<note place="margin">Vide de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat diſt <hi>1,</hi> Quia paſsus.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayeth of baptiſm, that we are not baptized that we may ceaſe from ſinning, but becauſe we have left off to ſinne, and have our hearts waſhed, and clenſed. <hi>Non ideo abluimur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De poenitentia</note> 
               <hi>ut deſinamus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquere, ſeà quia deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imus, &amp; corde loti ſumus.</hi> The table is ever ſpread for the ſoule, when the word is preached, and the Sacrament miniſtred.</p>
            <p>We bring with us actuall faith to feede upon him, whom by habituall faith we retain dwelling alreadie in us. <hi>Familiaris loquendi modus eſt ut fieri dicatur quod factum obſignatur.</hi> It is a familiar kinde of ſpeaking
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18916:32"/> to ſay that a thing is in doing, which alreadie done is ſealed and confirmed,<note place="margin">De ſacram. pag. <hi>68.</hi>
               </note> ſayth <hi>Whitakers.</hi> Fourthly, the nature of the gift is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. Any man will behaue himſelf other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe when he receiueth a Iewell out of the princes hand, nor when he is receiving a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, &amp; is in the act of feaſting with him. Chriſt and his Apoſtles knewe after what maner we ſhould behaue our ſelues at this banquet, that we neede not to goe learn courteſie at the court.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, that men bow to the chair of eſtate,<note place="margin">The argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t drawn from ceremonies of court anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> or the Princes letter, or ſeale, without injurie done to the Kings perſon. Yea the honour is conveyed to the Prince by the chair of eſtate, or the ſeale. <hi>Doctor Abbots</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Biſhop</hi> in another purpoſe may ſerue here verie well.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 1215.</note> 
               <hi>It ſhould ſeeme strange that formalities obſerved to Princes in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r courts, for maieſtie and royall eſtate ſhould be made patterns of religious devotions to be practiſed in the Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De civit. dei. l. <hi>2,</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth that civill courteſies often are grounded upon baſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, or peſtiferous flatterie. Hence it is that ſome countries miſlike the courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of other countries. <hi>Conon</hi> an heathen refuſed to adore <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> after the manner of the Perſians.</p>
            <p>Next the bowing to the chair of eſtate or to the ſeal of the prince, is but a civil worſhip for a politick end, to teſtifie homage &amp; allegiance. Doctor Abbots in defence of <hi>Perkins,</hi> ſayeth <hi>It is holden for a matter of princely Maieſtie, that there be a reverence performed to theſe things which ſerue in a ſpeciall manner for the Princes uſe.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18916:32"/> On the other ſide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 121<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>no ſuch duetie is done to the Princes Image.</hi> It is thought good by the State, that the Maieſtie of Princes be uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by ſuch meanes, becauſe they are but weake mortall men. But God needeth not any ſuch props to hold up his maieſtie, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil he haue any worſhip conveyed to him mediatelie by anie creature never ſo holy, or of whatſoever uſe. The ſacraments are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to ſeales, but not in every reſpect. The ſacraments haue all their force and power from the word, ſo hath not the Kings ſeale from the Charter. The word is of it ſelfe firme and ſure without the ſacraments, ſo is not the Charter without the ſeale. A ſeale maketh things authenticall, as meaſures, clothes, grants, or the like. The ſacraments are annexed to the word, not to make the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd more authenticall, but to confirme our faith. The outward ſignes of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are made for us, not we for them. And as one ſayth, as they are the plaineſt part of Divinitie, ſo they come loweſt to our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, and capacitie. When we heard the word, we were ſealed with the Spirit, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 1.13. The holy Spirit is the ſeale or ſignet ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us to redemption, the graces of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are the ſeales ſealed, or printed upon us. The holy Spirit ſealeth unto us Chriſt, and all his benefites, and properly aſſureth us of them, ſometime by the word, and ſometime by the ſacrament as outward meanes. The outward meanes are to bee reverenced, but not to be adored.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18916:33"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t taken from bowing before the arke an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note>It is alledged that we may bow before the Sacramental bread, and wine, becauſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God bowed before the ark. We anſwer, they bowed not for reverence of the arke, but to God dwelling, or ſitting in the arke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Cherubims. God was after an extraordinarie, and ſingular manner preſent in the arke, delivering oracles. For this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular preſence of God in the arke the Temple was built, and al the implements therof made. God promiſed to heare his people, when they ſhould turne them toward this Temple. So they bowed toward the arke, toward the Temple, wherein the arke was, toward the mountain wheron the Temple was ſituate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Gods preſence in the ark, in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wherein the arke was, &amp; which was ſituate vpon the mountaine. They bowed toward the Temple, not as toward a particular thing, but as toward a particular place of preſence. The bread is a particular thing, not a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar place of preſence, wherein God may be ſaid to ſitt, or dwell, or from whence he promiſeth to heare our prayers.</p>
            <p>There is no ſuch place of preſence now under the New teſtament. The arke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God dwelt or ſate, was a type of Chriſts manhood, not yet exiſting, and of the Godhead dwelling in the manhood. The Temple alſo, Iohn the ſecond chapter and the nineteene verſe. But now under the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament we are directed to direct our worſhip to that place where the Godhead is dwelling, in the Manhood exiſting, that is, to the heauen where Chriſts Manhood is.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:18916:33"/>
            <p>Yee will ſay,<note place="margin">Improper ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oration is idolatrous.</note> we may reverence the bread as a ſigne of Chriſts body by way of repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is, as if his body, howbeit abſent were preſent in the bread, or under the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of bread, and all the honour that wee would doe to the body of Chriſt, as if it were preſent, we doe before, and about the bread, as in a Comedie, all the honour done to him that repreſenteth the King, is accounted done properly to the King, not to him that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth, but improperly. Sicklyke to an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour: and after the ſame maner to an emptie coffin at funeralls. We anſwer, that we owe no adoration to any creature either properly, or improperly. A repreſentation of Chriſts body actiuely to the communicant, that is to repreſent his body to be received, we acknowledge: but a repreſentation of Chriſts body paſſiuely, that is to ſtand in Chriſts roome to receiue adoration from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant, as a Vicegerent of Chriſt abſent, we doe not acknowledge. For that were to giue a portion of divine honour to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to make it Chriſts Vicegerent when wee worſhip him. By this reaſon wee might not onely kneele, but kiſſe the ſacrament, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our ſpeech and prayer toward it, as the Ieſuite doth, when fixing his eyes upon a Crucifixe in his Sermon, hee directeth his ſpeech to Chriſt. To this kinde of worſhip many referre the convey of civill worſhip to the Prince, by the chaire of eſtate. But it is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to one particular, to wit, bowing.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:18916:34"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Coniunct a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration, or proper reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue of the ſignes are intended in the act, and both are idolatrous.</note>Yee will ſay, yee intend not this repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but conſider Chriſt as preſent, as the Papiſt conſidereth the ſamplar, or perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as preſent, as clothed with the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or ſhining in the Image, that is, preſent <hi>Secundum eſſe repreſentativum, non ſecundum eſſe reale,</hi> that is, by meere repreſentation onely. This coniunct adoration is like the coadorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the purple robe wherewith the King is clothed, or of the Popes ſhooe, when the Pope is adored, or any ſubmiſſion, or ſupplication made unto him. But God will not bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped according to our apprehenſions. We make an idoll of him if we apprehend him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then he is. The ſacrament cannot be the robe of that body which is in the heavens and not in the bread: and therefore the bread cannot be worſhipped <hi>concomitanter</hi> with the body of Chriſt upon a meere apprehenſion. There is no adoration of any created thing with the Godhead, but onely of the manhead of Chriſt united perſonally to the Godhead. Therefore <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> an old heretick, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the manhead of Chriſt to be a diſtinct perſon from the Godhead, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing averring that the manhead ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored with the Godhead, was condemned in the Councell of Epheſus. The body it ſelfe of Chriſt were not to be adored if it were not perſonally united to his Godhead. I know the underſtanding Formaliſt denieth in words both the improper and coniunct adoration. But we are now examining the private intent of the communicants, and who doubteth but many apprehend Chriſts, body to bee either
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18916:34"/> preſent in apprehenſion, or repreſented as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or really preſent in the bread when they kneele. Did not one of our Barons proteſt, that he kneeled not for reverence of the bread, but becauſe it was a ſigne of Chriſts body? What was that to ſay, but that he would not adore the ſimple bread, but that hee would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the ſacramentall bread? but after what manner? whether improperly, or coniunctly, or reſpectiuely? I thinke he could ſcarce tell himſelfe. What may we then iudge of many in the land? The formaliſt kneeling accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the intent of the act in regard of the divine myſterie, that is, of the ſacramentall receiving of Chriſts body and blood, adoreth either the body of Chriſt and the ſignes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctly, as <hi>obiectum quod, totale &amp; adaequatum,</hi> or els diſiunctly the ſignes, as the material ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, <hi>obiectum quod,</hi> and the body of Chriſt onely by conſequence, as <hi>obiestum quo,</hi> the reaſon wherefore he adoreth the ſignes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and directly <hi>in recto,</hi> as they ſpeake, and the ſamplar but indirectly, <hi>in obliquo.</hi> There is no other regard either of praier, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like thing expreſſed in the act, which may lead us to thinke that improper adoration was intended. And of the two laſt I cannot ſee how the proper reſpectiue can be intended, ſeeing they are then uſing the ſignes to the end whereunto they were appointed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them <hi>in actu exercito,</hi> as they are then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting Chriſts body. Whereas the proper reſpectiue is given to the ſignes, as to things ſacred. As when the Papiſt paſſing by the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, uncovereth his head conſidering it only
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18916:35"/> generaly and confuſedly, as a thing ſacred. But when he conſidereth the Image, as it is an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage <hi>actu exercito</hi> repreſenting the thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and intendeth to adore in it, or before it the ſamplar or perſon repreſented, then hee kneeleth: for their proper reſpectiue adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they call veneration, ſuch honour as they giue to the book of the Goſpell, or ſacred veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, ſayth <hi>Swarez,</hi> who calleth it <hi>adoratio ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraria.</hi> Howſoever it is with them, kneeling is ever a geſture of adoration, and never to bee uſed, but to God directly in abſolute adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Abſolute adoration we call that which is given to perſons, or intellectuall creatures for ſome intrinſick excellencie in them. Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue we call that which is determined in ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and dead creatures, reſteth in them, and is properly given them which are honoured <hi>per ſe</hi> by themſelues, howbeit <hi>propter aliud</hi> for ſome extrinſick excelencie out of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; inherent in the ſamplar, or thing repreſented, and conſequently honour redoundeth to the ſamplar by conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Obiectum a quo ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficative</hi> anſwered.</note>Put the caſe the Formaliſt were free of the former two intentions, that is, to adore ſignes, either coniunctly or reſpectiuely, and that it were true whereunto he fleeth, as unto his laſt refuge, that the bread and wine are <hi>obiectum à quo ſignificativè,</hi> that is, an actiue obiect moving us to worſhip the thing ſignified: which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth not from the adoration which <hi>Durandus Holcot,</hi> and <hi>Pic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Mirandula</hi> giue to Images: for they adore not images the obiect of their adoration; but only in their preſence, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them worſhip the ſamplar. Their adoratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:18916:35"/> is as abſtract from the image as theirs can be from the elements, neither can Doctor <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> ſhew any difference. The outward action is exerciſed materially before the image, the intention of worſhip is directed to the ſamplar in their underſtanding. So the image was only <hi>obiectum a quo ſignificative</hi> to them in regard of the inward aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction. And yet we condemne them for exerciſing the natural action of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adoration before the image, or at the preſence of the image.<note place="margin">Reſolut. pag. <hi>161.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>M. Lindſay</hi> ſayeth that there is a difference between images the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, &amp; the works of God, the word of God, and the ſacraments. But manie of the Engliſh formaliſts approue images as lawfull obiects to ſtirre up the memorie, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer to <hi>Morton</hi> doth teſtifie. And they haue reaſon: for if they condemned images, as ſignes invented by men, unfit, and unlawfull for wakening up of the memorie, and putting them in minde of ſome pious dutie, they muſt alſo condemne the ſigne of the croſſe, the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, and other ſignificant rites invented by man. Now if they may be lawful obiects to ſtirr up the memorie, what can hinder adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before them, more then before other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obiects. <hi>Si exemplaria ipſa per ſe ſint digna adoratione, quid obſtare poteſt praeſentia imaginis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 798.</note> 
               <hi>quo minus adorari poſſint,</hi> ſaith <hi>Swarez.</hi> So in the caſe of adoration there is no difference. In the caſe of eſtimation, or veneration, &amp; inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they differ. We eſteem more of Gods works then the workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip of men. We owe vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, a decent &amp; comly uſage to Gods word &amp; ſacraments, which we ought not to images.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18916:36"/> They are alſo ordayned by God for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and ſo are not images. But to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore God in them, by them, or before them by direction, is forbidden as well as adoration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore images. Otherwiſe we ſhould fall downe before everie green tree, before an aſſe, or a toade, or any other vile creature, when they worke as objects upon our minds, and moue us to conſider Gods goodnes, wiſdome and power. We haue to conſider, that when a man is conſidering the inviſible things of God in the workmanſhip of an aſſe, tree, toade or any other creature, he is not then praying, or prayſing except by ejaculations, which may occurre in al our actions, but he is meditating, and contemplating. For if I ſhould adore, that is pray, or praiſe God upon my knees in the meane time, when I am poring with the eyes both of body &amp; minde upon a tree, or a toade, I ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found two exerciſes, or be thought to adore the aſſe, the toade, or the tree, or God in,<note place="margin">De adoratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne lib. <hi>3</hi> diſp. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> or by the aſſe, toade or tree. <hi>Vaſques the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite</hi> doubteth not to averre, that not an image onely, or an holy thing may be worſhipped, with the ſame adoration that is given to God, but alſo any thing in the world, the ſunne, the moone, the ſtars, a ſtock, a little ſtone, or a ſtraw. We are not far from this horrible er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, if we fall down to worſhip God before his creatures, when they put us in remembrance of him, or when we contemplat his properties in them.<note place="margin">Reſolutions p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. <hi>162.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>M. Lindſay</hi> himſelf changeth the phraſe of ſpeech to ſhun this abſurditie. For he ſayth, <hi>To bow down when we haue ſeen the works of God, when we haue heard the word, and when we
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18916:36"/> receiue the ſacraments to adore him, when by his works the word and ſacraments we are taught to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore, is neyther to bow downe to an Idoll, nor to worſhip God in an Idol.</hi> Why doth he not ſay, <hi>when we haue received the ſacraments,</hi> as he ſayd of the other two, <hi>when we haue ſeene the workes of God, when we haue heard the word,</hi> or why doth he not ſay, <hi>when we ſee the works of God, when we heare the word, and when we receiue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,</hi> as he ſhould haue done, if he would haue ſhowen the difference betwixt images, the works of God, the word of God, and the ſacraments. For the works, and word of God are objects ſignificant, when we ſee and heare the ſame. So if we may fall down to worſhip God, when we ſee the ſacrament, becauſe it is <hi>obiectum a quo ſignificative,</hi> we may do the like when we hear the word, or in private worſhip, when we ſee the creatures, and conſider the workmanſhip of God in them: for theſe are not images or inventions of men. The ground of this error is the confounding of two exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, prayer, or praiſe, and meditation, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation. If I were reading a paſſage of ſcripture, and meditating upon it, I adore not then upon my knees, becauſe I am then appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending, and conſidering what is read, and adore not till that exerciſe be ended. When it is ended, if I finde my ſelf moued to pray or to giue thanks, I pore not ſtil with the ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of my minde, and body upon the book, but turn me to a wall, or a chair, or a bed, or any other thing caſually placed before me, yea perhaps before the book it ſelf, but caſually, as before any other thing. For I am not then gathering
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18916:37"/> leſſons or inſtructions. For that exerciſe is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and this time it is not fit. As it fareth with the book of grace, ſo doeth it with the booke of nature. When I am reading in the booke of nature beholding an aſſe, a tree, or a toade, or any other workmanſhip of God, and conſidering in it his goodnes, power, wiſdome, it is an object moving me to praiſe, &amp; thanke God, but not in that exerciſe. For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n I ſhal both ſtill behold and adore. Now, if we may not do this with the works of God in private worſhip, we may not do it with the word read or preached, or the ſacramental ſignes in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhip. For when we are hearing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, and conſidering, we are receiving in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from the objects of the eye and the eare, and we are then in another employment then when we are adoring. Farther the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are <hi>objectum a quo ſignificative</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly after the conſecration, as the papiſt and formaliſt both hold. Therefore all that are in the kirk ſhould kneel at the ſight of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated elements, euen long before they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, or approach to receiue, and the elements ſhould be lifted up, as the bread is among the papiſts at the elevation, to the ende they may be moued to inward devotion, and outward adoration by this <hi>obiectum a quo ſignificative.</hi> for now is the time of publick worſhip, and after their conſecration they haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their vertue to ſignifie. This adoration before a ſignificant object inſtructing the minde, or ſtirring up the memorie wil be found nothing different from improper adoration, which is by way of repreſentation. For I exerciſe the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18916:37"/> outward acts of adoration before that obiect, as a Vice gerent of the thing abſent ſignified by the ſame. For the Ieſuites ſay, they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip an image improperly, when they take it <hi>obiective,</hi> and make it the Vicegerent of the thing conſidered, as abſent, or diſtant. <hi>Swarez</hi> reckoning all the ſorts of adoration of images reduceth them to three, the improper worſhip of <hi>Durandus,</hi> and <hi>Holcot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>diſp.</hi> 51. 52. 53.</note> when the image is <hi>obiectum a quo ſignificatiue:</hi> the conjunct adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the image with the ſamplar: the proper reſpectiue of the image for the ſamplars ſake. So the improper by repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the firſt ſort. To adore then by direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before a creature, becauſe it is <hi>obiectum a quo ſignificative,</hi> is to adore it by way of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the thing ſignified, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all that ſervice before and about it, which I would performe, if the ſamplar were preſent, which kinde of adoration the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Formaliſt denyeth. And in deed the act of Perth beareth no ſuch thing: for to kneel in regard of ſo divine a myſterie, to wit, as is the receiuing of the body and bood of Chriſt ſacramentally is not to adore before the elements as <hi>obiectum a quo ſignificative</hi> the ſamplar, but to adore the elements themſelves with the thing ſignified. Thirdly, the el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments are not ſet before us, as <hi>obiectum a quo ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative</hi> only, to be preſented to the eye out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and by the eye to moue the minde,<note place="margin">De euchariſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> but we take, eate, drink. Therefore ſayth <hi>Beller<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Iſte fructus melius obtinetur videndo eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtiam in menſa, quam eam manducando. Nam du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manducatur continuo peril ſignificatio. At dum
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18916:38"/> cernitur, &amp; attente confideratur, ſemper repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, &amp; ſignificat promiſſiones Dei, etiamſi per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num integrum eam quis cernere vellet. Praeterea ſignificatio melius apprehenditur per oculos, quam per guſtandi ſenſum.</hi> The meate ſet before us at table, before it be uſed is an obiect moving us to praiſe God for his beneficence, but withall it is a ſubiect, whereupon we craue a bleſſing to be powred, becauſe we are to uſe it. Next we bleſſe, or giue thanks, not kneeling: but in the verie uſe and act of eating and drinking, none did ever ſay grace, as wee uſe to ſpeake, farre leſſe kneele, no not among the moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, or yet the moſt ſuperſtitious. Theſe three things are ever to be diſtinguiſhed in the benefits of God, &amp; not to be confounded, preparation before the uſe, by prayer and thanksgiving, the uſe it ſelf, and thankſgiving after the uſe.</p>
            <p>There are ſome other ſhifts ſcarſe worth the anſwering, therefore I doe but lightly touch them. From the uncovering of the head, a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of ſimple reverence, &amp; that among ſome nations onelie, can no good argument be drawen for kneeling,<note place="margin">A fardel of pretences an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> which is a geſture of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oration among all nations, neither in civil, nor religious uſe. I wil not kneel to everie one to whom I uncover my head. A provincial ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod at London 1603 ordained the head to be uncovered, when their ſervice is read in the church, yet I think they would not haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned kneeling. And are not the words of Chriſt, which he uttered at the firſt ſupper, as much to be reverenced? For that ſame voice ſoundeth through all the tables of the world
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18916:38"/> Siclyke when they reaſon from the reſpectiue veneration of the name of Ieſus, by lifting the tap, or making a leg, which beſide that it is ſuperſtitious in giving more reverence to the name of Ieſus, then to the name of Chriſt, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Redeemer, ſo is it not an argument for kneeling, which is a geſture of adoration. Whereas it is ſaid, we may receiue upon our knees, that which we may craue in Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhip upon our knees, is untrue. For the preacher may craue a bleſſing upon his knees, and yet when he findeth and feeleth the bleſſing in his preaching, he may not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore upon his knees. Siclyke the hearer may craue a bleſſing to his hearing, and yet in the act of hearing may not adore upon his knees. Further, if I may receiue kneeling in publike worſhip, that benefit which I craved in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhip, then in privat worſhip I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a benefit upon my knees, which I craved in private worſhip upon my knees: for the difference of the place, publike and private, altereth not the nature of worſhip. For the place is but a circumſtance, common to all our actions. So in whatſoever place he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the benefit, he may receiue it upon his knees; and ſo becauſe he craved daylie food, by this reaſon he ought to adore upon his knees, when he receiueth his food, and is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying the benefite, eating, and drinking, which groſſe abſurditie the groſſeſt may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. Humilitie of minde is required not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all religious exerciſes, the hearing of the word, receiving of the ſacramenss, executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the cenſures of the church, but alſo in all our
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18916:39"/> actions. It will not follow therefore, that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of our body, or adoration is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red where humility of mind is required, To conclude, as I asked before, when I examined the publick intent, ſo now I aske at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants pretending many private intents, what is the reaſon that they kneele, when they reciue, eate, Chriſts fleſh, and drink his blood in the Lords Supper, more then when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, eate his fleſh, and drink his blood at the hearing of the word, everie one ſeverally, as they beleeue and finde the like, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more fervent motions, if it be not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the elements, or of the thing ſignified, and the elements, which is idolatry? Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber beſide, that whatſoever be thy private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, thy action muſt be conſtrued according to the publick. If the publick be idolatrous, thy geſture is idolatrous. <hi>Ex voluntate iubentis pendet intentio exequentis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">lib. de praecep. &amp; diſpen.</note> ſayth <hi>Bernard.</hi> Yee haue ſeen my reaſons, and anſweres, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alledge not the naked and bare aſſertions of ſome Divines, who haue not written ſo hardly of this geſture of kneeling, becauſe they haue not been troubled with it, as the Divines in our neighbour Church, who haue been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to examine and conſider it more narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but let reaſon meet reaſon. <hi>Ratio cum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione concertet.</hi> For even a Ieſuite <hi>Maldona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> doth confeſſe, that <hi>Rationum efficatia est prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantior omni authoritate, niſi divina. Mortoni Apologia part.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſitter is acceſsarie to the ſin of the kneeler.</note> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>The ſitter is acceſſorie to the ſinne of the kneeler. Firſt, he endureth the kneeler by his preſence, and maketh him think, that his knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18916:39"/> is neither ſcandalous nor idolatrous. You ſay, your ſitting condemneth his kneeling. No ſuch matter. But in communicating with him, you approue it as indifferent, as when ye ſit in time of prayer after ſermon, when ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is kneeling, or ſtanding. For ſhall you communicate with an idolater in the very act of his idolatry, and not be acceſſorie in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing it with your preſence. If you doe damne it as ſcandalous, or idolatrous, why communicate you with him? If you build up that which you deſtroyed, you make your ſelfe a treſpaſſer. The Apoſtle forbiddeth the Corinthians to converſe, or eate with a brother idolater, 1 Cor. 5. and yet you will eate and drink with him, when hee is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the very act. The Apoſtle forbiddeth not ſocietie with him in publick Aſſemblies, but onely in private, &amp; where he committeth the act, till he be reclaimed. Next, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant with the kneeler caſteth himſelfe into tentation, by ſetting before him an evil example, which may enduce him to doe the like, ſpecially if the kneeler be a perſon of any credit and countenance. Many are diſquieted with the ſight of a monſter, or carcaſſe many moneths after. It is an evill token when you can be ſo well content to ſee ſuch a monſter in our kirk, and your heart not riſe within you. If you ſhould preſent your ſelfe to the maſſe in the ſame manner, and with the ſame liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, cuſtome would ſo harden the heart, that in the end you would halt with the lame, and conforme in every point. It will creepe like a Ring-worme: feemeth it now tollerable,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18916:40"/> the next day it will ſeeme holy, and the third day neceſſarie. So bewitching ſinnes are ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and ſuperſtition. Thirdly, you are partaker of an Idoll feaſt. Start not at this I ſay: for the ſacrament of the Lords Supper may be turned into an idoll feaſt, and hath been a more abhominable feaſt then ever was any among the heathens. And howbeit there may be ſome difference betwixt the formaliſts and the papiſts, ariſing upon the diverſitie of inward opinions and conceits of Chriſts reall preſence in the elements, yet if both their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures be idolatrous in their owne kindes, the Lords ſupper is made an idoll feaſt. <hi>Non ad Diabolum pertinet quis iſto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de pastor.</note> 
               <hi>vel illo modo erret, omnes errantes vult quibuſlibet erroribus.</hi> It is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Divell whether a man erre this way or that way, whatſoever way they erre, all that bee in error, hee ſeeketh to bee his. Fourthly, the communicant advanceth this innovation, and ſetteth forward this groſſe corruption by his preſence and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the kneeler. For if the kneelers were left to themſelues, they would be aſhamed of themſelues, wheras now they are comforted &amp; hardened in their ſin, &amp; ſome follow their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Ioanne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſol.</note> 
               <hi>Fides pura mora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non patitur ut apparuerit ſcorpius, illico conterendus eſt.</hi> Pure faith ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth no delayes. As ſoon as the ſcorpion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, it is to be bruiſed ſaith <hi>Hierom.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie a confuſion of geſtures lawfull, and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is brought into the Lords table, ſome ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting like ghueſts at a feaſt, as Chriſt, and his Apoſtles ſate, others like ſupplicants kneeling, and adoring vpon their knees. This confuſion
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18916:40"/> is not like that varietie of geſture in time of prayer, when ſome ſitt, ſome ſtand, ſome kneele. For all the three geſtures are there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different. But not ſo heere, This confuſion of geſtures at the Lords table now is permitted onlie for a ſnare to bring thy feete, within the grin. For when all are brought in, then wil the formaliſts crie out. Confuſion of geſtures is intollerable, vniformitie, and conformitie is neceſſarie, as Doctor Sparke doeth in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion to vniformitie.<note place="margin">The act of Perth, and act of Parliament no warrant for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yee will pretend the act of Perth, and the act of Parliament ratifieng the ſame. But know yee not, that the decrees of councels, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies are not Goſpell, or determinations Evangelicall, as the Papiſts doe eſteeme them, who build their faith, and worſhip vpon the authoritie of the church. Is it not alſo well known, what were the proceedings of that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie, how the ſounder part was born down by the corrupter. If we ought to receave, whatſoever aſſemblies ſhould determin, be the proceedings never ſo vnjuſt, then wer we to be blamed, who rejected the councell of Trent, not onlie for their wicked decrees, but alſo for the nullities, and informalities in their proceeding. The Father of lies himſelf is not able to juſtifie that aſſemblie, and it cannot be defended, but with calumnies, and lies, which manie eye &amp; ear witneſſes can teſtifie. Though we ſitt not formallie, and judiciallie in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorie as Iudges over wicked, and vnlawfull aſſemblies. Yet, if we have anie judgement, we may, and ought to judge of aſſemblies, both of their procerdings, and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18916:41"/> leaſt vnder colour of Councels we ſuffet our ſelves to be ledde like a calfe by the noſe. <hi>Patientia aſinina eſt non curare, quid ei imponatur, aurum, an lutum</hi> ſayeth <hi>Peraldus.</hi> Farther I have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curring with me, the bodie of the church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> at leaſt three parts of the whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the particular congregations within the realme ſtanding out againſt the decrees of that aſſemblie, and adhering to their former practiſe which is according to the paterne, and to the confeſſion of faith, wherin this church profeſſeth the right vſe of Miniſtration of the Sacraments, and a deteſtation of all rites, and ceremonies, brought in by Antichriſt, or not warranted by the word of God. The bodie of the Kirk is of greater authoritie, then an aſſemblie, athough lawful, it being onlie a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative bodie, not the collective, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>augmentatiue body. <hi>Lex vigorem habet cum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus utentium approbatur.</hi> As for the act of Parliament, it is onely a ratification of the Act of Perth in favours of the kirk, as all ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of church acts are pretended to be. If the aſſemblie of Perth it ſelf, be not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the kirk of Scotland for one of her lawfull aſſemblies, nor the decrees and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances thereof iudged agreeable to the word of God, then the act of ratification is no bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or favour to the kirk. The kirk of Scotland refuſeth ſuch a benefit. <hi>Invito beneficium non datur.</hi> What freedom and libertie was in that Parliament, and how matters were caryed I doubt not, but ye haue ſufficiently painted forth in that booke, which is intituled. <hi>The courſe of conformitie.</hi> Eſay pronounceth a woe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18916:41"/> upon them that make heavie lawes. cha. 10.1. Seing Councels and parliaments may be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, either in their proceedings or decrees, let us ſtick to the word,<note place="margin">Enarrat. <hi>2.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> which muſt be the rule of our fayth and worſhip. <hi>Stet regula, &amp; quod pravum eſt corrigatur ad regulam,</hi> ſayth Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.<note place="margin">M. Knox co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical, which is now commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſsors as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Knox,</hi> that worthy inſtrument of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in our Church in a letter written to Matreſſe <hi>Anna Lock</hi> dated at Deepe the ſixt of April 1559, calleth the croſſe in baptiſme, and kneeling at the Lords table Diabolical inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. In his admonition directed to England, and printed Anno 1554, he ranketh kneeling at the Lords table, among the ſuperſtitions,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 31.</note> which prophane <hi>Chriſts</hi> true religion. When light did ſtriue with darknes in this realme, yet the Lord enlightened that worthie man for our benefit beyond his fellowes. Now we are turning light in darknes, &amp; commending that as moſt comely, &amp; commendable, which he condemned as diabolicall. There are yet ſome of his ſucceſſors in his ſtation aliue (<hi>M. R. Bruce,</hi> that faithful ſervant of God (who foretold, that the time would come, when the leaſt kitchin laſſe or ladd in Edinburgh would be tryed, and that by their own teachers, which we ſee come to paſſe this day. As his ſucceſſors haue forewarned us of theſe times of tryall, ſo haue they of iudgments. Heare, what that meeke man of God <hi>M. Robert Rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> ſaid.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:18916:42"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rollocke on the Paſsion printed in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh pag. <hi>345.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>WOe to them, whom hee forbiddeth his ſervants goe vnto: Woe to us, if we ſay once, goe not to Edinburgh: Woe is them, and woe to that town, where the Lord forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his meſſengers to goe. Beware of this, that the Lord ſay not to his meſſenger, goe to the north, or ſouth, but goe not to Edinburgh. For then ſhall wrath, and distruction light on it.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Cyprianus lib. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>QVod ſi nec minima de mandatis Dominicis licet ſoluere, quanto magis tam magna, tam grandia tam ad ipſum Dominicae paſſionis, &amp; nostrae redemptionis Sacramentum pertinentia fas non eſt infringere.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18916:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
